<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A most comfortable exposition of the last and most difficult part of the prophecie of Daniel from the 26. verse of the 11. chap, to the end of the 12. chapter. Wherin the restoring of the Iewes and their callinge to the faith of Christ, after the utter overthrow of their three last enemies, is set forth in livelie coulours, by the labour and studie of that bright and worthie man of God, Thomas Brightman Englishman &amp; once fellowe of Queenes College in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Brightman, Thomas, 1562-1607.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16852</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3753</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117062</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852277</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852277</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17593</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16852)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17593)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1129:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A most comfortable exposition of the last and most difficult part of the prophecie of Daniel from the 26. verse of the 11. chap, to the end of the 12. chapter. Wherin the restoring of the Iewes and their callinge to the faith of Christ, after the utter overthrow of their three last enemies, is set forth in livelie coulours, by the labour and studie of that bright and worthie man of God, Thomas Brightman Englishman &amp; once fellowe of Queenes College in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Brightman, Thomas, 1562-1607.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>114 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Successors of G. Thorp],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 3753a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Daniel XI-XII --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17593:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17593:1"/>
            <p>A MOST COMFORTABLE EXPOSITION OF The laſt and moſt difficult part of the prophecie of Daniel from the 26. verſe of the 11. chap, to the end of the 12. chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherin the reſtoring of the Iewes and their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge to the faith of Christ, after the utter over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of their three laſt enemies, is ſet forth in livelie coulours,</hi> By the labour and ſtudie of that bright and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie man of God, THOMAS BRIGHTMAN Engliſhman &amp; once fellowe of Queenes College in Cambridge.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom: 11.25.26.</hi>
               </bibl> J would not brethren, that ye ſhould bee ignorant of this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, that partly obſtinacie is come to Iſrael, vntil the fulnes of the gentiles be come in: and ſo all Iſrael ſhall bee ſaved, as it is written, The Deliverer ſhall come out of Sion, and ſhall turn awaie the ungodlines from Iacob.</q>
            <p>Anno 1635.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17593:2"/>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:17593:2"/>
            <head>To the friendly READER</head>
            <p>ALthough the revealing of the Revelation and the ſong of ſonges doe yeeld cleere and notable arguments, ſufficiently to make knowne the happie and longed for voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Iewes, yet the due regard of ſuch a divine myſterie doth require that we bring forth &amp; laie to every litle ſparke, taken from the aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of God, which maie yeeld more cleere and evide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t proofe of that truth which mortall men doe not yet ſufficiently conceive &amp; ſee into. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold therefore how this truth is confirmed not of one or two, but of three ſuch wittneſſes, as are beyond all exception. Daniel is added to Iohn and Salomon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1.2. <hi>With.</hi> 10. 14.</note> who among the viſions of God almightie, doe plainly teſtifie that this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of his nation to be performed in the laſt times was alſo revealed, what ſpeciall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the good <hi>&amp;</hi> great God made of all theſe, doe thoſe ſingular commendations teſtifie, which the Scriptures have honoured them withall. Iohn he is the diſciple who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus loved, Salomon was the king beloved of his God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.23.</note>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:17593:3"/> whom his name was called Iedediah;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehe.</hi> 13.26. <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.11.19.</note> 2. Sam. 12.25, Daniel alſo is a man of deſires, becauſe in his time he was moſt accepted and beloved of God. It muſt not therfore ſeeme ſtrange, if God made known his ſecrets unto them after a ſpeciall maner,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.14. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.12.</note> for the ſecret of the Lord is preſent to them that feare him. Vnited forces do allwais beſt prevaile, and the more helpes they aſſociate and ioyne together, the ſtronger they are, A three fold coard is not eaſily broken.</p>
            <p>Although therfore thou doe ſomtime doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinglie read over the Revelation of Iohn, &amp; the ſonge of Salomon for the newnes and ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the matter, yet when by Daniels coming in, ſuch an admirable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of Scripture, giveth ſuch cleere lighte to confirme the matter in hand, feare not to embrace the truth with thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnes unto God: for here all theſe, not by mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall conſpiration, but by divine inſpiration, doe proclaime one and the ſame thinge.</p>
            <p>How much alſo Daniels teſtimonie is to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of in this matter, thou ſhalt farre better perceive by his owne words wel underſtood, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by mine, as the e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuing expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plainly ſheweth.</p>
            <p>That truly is of great weight that Daniels prophecie is deputed and appointed for the Iewes, to whom notwithſtanding he bringeth no comfort, if that reſurrection ſpoken of 12.2. be underſtood of the laſt and generall reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, properly ſo called, which without all doubte both in matter and time doth fall-in
<pb facs="tcp:17593:3"/> together with their deliveraunce in verſe. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde then after the Iewes three laſt enemies be vtterly overthrowne; that is to ſaie, The Romane empire, which is called the King ch. 11.36. and is deſcribed by his properties verſe 37.38.39. and the Saracens, whom he noteth and nameth, The King of the South verſ. 40. and laſtly, the Turkiſh empire ſtiled with the title of the King of the North verſ. 40. &amp;c. Behold I ſaie, a plaine and cleere pourtraiture of the Iewes vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not onely vndertaken and begun 44.45. but conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and perfect ch. 12.1.2.3. where it ſhall bee made manifeſt (<hi>I</hi> think) without obſcuritie. That the reſurrection there, is the full reſtoring of the Iewiſh nation out of the duſt of deſtruction and their calling to the faith in Chriſt, wherby thoſe that are dead in ſinne are truly raiſed up againe according to that of the Apoſtle, If the caſting away of them be the reconciling of the world, what ſhall the receiving of them be, but life from the dead. Rom. 11.15.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And that the mindes of good men maie the leſſe be diſquieted in the expectation of ſo great a felicity and happines. Lo the very times of this deliveraunce opened to thee, as well of it begun whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tidings out of the Eaſt ſhall trouble the Turk verſ. 7. and 11. as when fulfilled, when the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh name and empire both ſhall bee vtterly abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, The greatnes of the Kingdomes vnder the whole heaven ſhalbee given to the people of the Saints of the moſt high, verſ. 12. True it is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17593:4"/> indeed that almoſt all theſe thinges are otherwiſe caried and applied by interpreters very wel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of the Church: but Truth is ever wel accepted and enterteined of the ingenuous, to which none can preſcribe a rule, or overrule, not ſpace of times, of patronage (or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority) of perſons,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Virgin. Velan. c. <hi>1.</hi> Auguſt. de lib. ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitr. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> as Tertullian ſpeaks well. Yea, if a ſcandall be taken (or ariſe) becauſe of the truth, it is more, profitable to permitt the ſcandall, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the truth ſhould be left. He doth ſparingly refute other mens opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, but mildly after his maner alwaies, where they prejudice and hinder the truth.</p>
            <p>The controverſy is cheifly concerning Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus, whom he endevoureth to proove by a multitude of weighty reaſons, That he muſt of neceſſitie be excluded out of every particle of this prophecie which he hath here vndertake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to handle. Aſſuredly he bringeth admirable light to the right vnderſtanding of the whole prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Daniel. Weighing then all thinges in an equall ballance, lay apart all prejudice againſt the truth diſcovered, and pray earneſtly with mee. That the Deliverer may come out of Sion, who may vtterly overthrow his enemies, the Beaſt with Gog and Magog, and that he may thorowly turne away vngodlines from Iacob. Farewel.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:17593:4"/>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>The text of the 11. Chapter of Daniel from verſ. 36. to the end.</bibl>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>36</hi>
                        </bibl> ANd the King ſhall doe according to his will, and he ſhall exalt himſelfe, and magnifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe above every god, and ſhall ſpeake marveilous things againſt the God of gods, and ſhall proſper till the indignation be accompliſhed: for that that is determined, ſhall be done.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>37.</hi>
                        </bibl> Neither ſhall he regard the god of his fathers, nor the deſire of women, nor regard any god: for he ſhall magnifie himſelfe above all.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>38.</hi>
                        </bibl> But in his eſtate ſhall hee honour the God of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and a God whom his fathers knew not, ſhall hee honour with gold, and ſilver, and with precious ſtones, and pleaſant things.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>39.</hi>
                        </bibl> Thus ſhall hee doe in the most ſtrong holds with a ſtrange god, whom he ſhall acknowledge, <hi>and</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe with glory: and hee ſhall cauſe them to rule ever many, and ſhall divide the land for gaine.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>40.</hi>
                        </bibl> And at the time of the end ſhall the King of the South puſh at him, and the King of the North ſhall come against him like a whirlewinde, with charets and with horſemen, and with many ſhips, and he ſhall enter into the countreys, and ſhall overflow and paſſe over.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>41.</hi>
                        </bibl> Hee ſhall enter alſo into the glorious land, and many <hi>countreys</hi> ſhall bee overthrowne: but theſe ſhall eſcape out of his hand, <hi>even</hi> Edom and Moab, and the chiefe of the children of Ammon.</p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:17593:5"/>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>42.</hi>
                        </bibl> He ſhall ſtretch foorth his hand alſo vpon the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, and the land of Egypt ſhall not eſcape.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>43.</hi>
                        </bibl> But he ſhall have power over the treaſures of gold and ſilver and over all the precious things of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt: and the Libyans, and the Ethiopians <hi>ſhall be</hi> at his ſteppes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>44.</hi>
                        </bibl> But tidings out of the East, and out of the North ſhall trouble him: therefore hee ſhall goe forth with great fury to destroy, and vtterly to make away many.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>45.</hi>
                        </bibl> And hee ſhall plant the tabernacles of his palace betweene the ſeas in the glorious holy mountaine, yet hee ſhall come to his end, and none ſhall helpe him.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>Let the words of my mouth and the meditation of my heart be acceptable in thy ſight O Lord my rock and my Redeemer.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <div type="analysis">
                  <head>THE ANALYSIS <hi>or Reſolution.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>DAniel recordeth things done in the firſt ſix chapters afterward in the reſt of the booke, viſions and revelations ſhewed to him: wherin is diſcloſed, what the people of the Iewes are to expect from that time to the very laſt end. Of the Revelations he firſt propoundeth the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall type of thinges to come in Chap: 7. in thoſe following he vſeth a larger declaration of the firſt, both as it did agree with the next times in regard either of the enemies chap. 8. or of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17593:5"/> Meſſias in cha. 9. As alſo it did agree to all times by a continued order and ſucceſſion from his owne time to the full deliveraunce of his nation. Of this laſt and plentifull Prophecie the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſet downe in the tenth chapt. then after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the thinge it ſelf in the two followinge chapters 11. and 12. From the beginning of the 11. chap. vnto this place the matters of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians and Grecians are ſo manifeſtly, particularly, and expreſſly foreſhewed, that in very deed, it may ſeeme rather a Hiſtorie then a prophecie. That which remaineth doth partly ſhewe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oppreſſors of the people of the Iewes, in this Chap. partly that wiſhed end of all their troubles in the following.</p>
                  <p>There are three oppreſſors ſett downe, The firſt a certaine Kinge deſcribed, without anie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of his dominion how farre it ſtretched, but ſummarily both of an unlimited power to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtrangers, moſt proude and proſperous till the appointed time verſ. 36. and alſo towards his owne, a contemner of his Countries and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers religion, without naturall affections, and exalting himſelf above all, verſ. 37. After perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly as he ſhould be famous for ſome ſpeciall acts, partly in the matter concerning Religion verſ. 38. and beginning of the next, and partly in politicke affaires, in the later part of verſ. 39. The ſecond is the King of the South verſ. 40. The third is the King of the North, who is hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pye in his preparation verſ. 40. in his proceeding
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17593:6"/> verſ. 41. and largenes of his dominion ver. 42.43. but is unhappye in the feare of dolefull tidinges, in his wicked purpoſe and reſolution of minde, v. 44. and laſt of all in his going forth and end verſ. 45.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="exposition">
                  <head>THE SCHOLIA or Expoſition.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>Verſ. 36.</bibl> And the King ſhall doe what him liſt, or according to his will.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>WEe have often times made mention of Daniel in the Revelation and the Canticles, whoſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie what force it hath to thoſe thinges for which we alledged, it, cannot be ſufficiently vnderſtood, except we repeate it from the beginning and take vpon us the full handling of a very obſcure place of ſcripture, and much controverted amongſt learned men: which truly I doe the more willingly vndertake, becauſe being holpen by the light of former expoſitions, we hope we ſhalbe able to bring ſomthing by Gods aſſiſtaunce to cleere the truth and bring it to light. Neither doe I doubt but it will be very acceptable to the godlie and learned to ſee Daniels, conſent with the reſt, and the lovelie face of the truth to be brought vpon the ſtage in open view, with whoſe bewtie the moſt heavenlie minded are eſpecially raviſhed, yea and which even the vulgar ſort of men, though vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkilfull beholders and judges of beawtie are alſo aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed therat. Every viſion hath difficultie in it, but he muſt have leiſure at will, that vndertaketh the whole work: but theſe laſt viſions being well vnderſtood, on which doth reſt the expoſition of the former, thoſe alſo that goe before may be eaſily conceived.</p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:17593:6"/>
                  <p>We begin the expoſition from the 36. verſe, becauſe there are not manie thinges in the former verſes need to ſtaie or hinder the Reader: but thoſe which followe are much doubted of, whether they belong to Antiochus E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanes, or to ſome other Kinge. Wel and rightly in my judgment doth Calvin avouch, That it can by no meanes be referred to Antiochus. Thoſe thinges that followe doe not anie wiſe agree: for how ſhould he doe what he liſt, by exalting himſelfe above all that is God, whom the ſhippes of Chittim limited and preſcribed verſ. 30. Neither did the Kings of Egypt, being younge, attempte anie thinge againſt Antiochus: Neither was there anie King of the North, by whom he ſuſteined anie wrong to ſpeak of. Or if we ſhall make Antiochus himſelf the King of the North, as ſome interpreters doe: Neither doth the King of the South provoke him as it foloweth verſ. 40. Neither did he returne into Egypte after he was commaunded to depart by the Romanes as verſ. 30. before.</p>
                  <p>The hiſtorie recordeth that he went twice into Egypt as, 2. Maca. 5.1. About the ſame time Antiochus vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took his ſecond voyage into Egypt, wherin he doth admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably agree with Daniel; but of a third expedition not <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gry,</hi> or the leaſt mention in anie Authour that I could finde. The Authours of the books of the Macabees would have made ſome mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof if there had bene anie. Neither wold Ioſephus have let it paſſe, who after the retturne of Antiochus out of Egypte by reaſon of the Romanes threatning denounced, doth mention nothing at all that was againe attempted againſt that Countrie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death among the Perſians. Livie alſo, who ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth him to be reſtrained by Popilius the legate lib. 45. of his Epitomies abridgement, declareth him in the next book to be dead without doing anie other memorable exploite. Iuſtice alſo, after he had declared the tarnteſſe and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17593:7"/> rigour of Popilius, telleth us that Antiochus died aſſbone as he was returned into his Kingdome: was it poſſible ſuch a notable expedition could be taken in hand, wherin ſo manie nations were overthrowne and great alterations came to paſſe, as it followeth verſ. 40.41. In recording wherof all theſe Authors would not be faithfull and diligent, which yet notwitſtanding ſhould eſcape the truſt and diligence of all theſe Authours.</p>
                  <p>But thou wilt ſaie, Though the Hiſtorie be ſilente, yet divine Oracle without all exception, makes the matter playne and manifeſt, for ſo Daniel ſpeaketh before, verſ. 29. At the time appointed he ſhall againe invade the South, but it ſhall not be as the firſt expedition, or as the laſt, but by the leave of learned men, no ſuch thing is here intended, if we doe rightly expound or tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlate the word, which runneth thus, But the ſet time ſhall returne and he ſhall com into the South, and it ſhall not be as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, ſo alſo the later, for there is nothing more frequent then for the later doubled Caph, to anſwere the former, and to be the reddition or anſwere therunto: in which ſenſe the particle <hi>Ita,</hi> ſo, doth anſwere the word. <hi>Sicut or ut,</hi> as: And it ſhall be as the prieſt, ſo the people, &amp;c. Iſa. 24.2. And it ſhall as the righteous ſo the wicked. Gen. 18.25. you ſhall heare, as the ſmal, ſo the great. Deut. 1.17. and very manie of the like ſort; wherfore the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of Tremelius is to be corrected, But it ſhall not be as the firſt expedition or as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he later: for the Copulative particle rendred diſiunctively, and the note of the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude being taken propoſitively and not reſponſively or redditively as it ought, doth plainely ſhew of three voya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, againſt the truth (if I be not deceived) of all hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, and againſt the minde and meaninge of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet himſelfe. For is it anie waie likely, that Antiochus for feare of the people of Rome had caried away his whole armie out of Egypte, the Romanes after that ſhould either leave off the care of that Kingdome, or that he ſhould dare
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17593:7"/> againe to enterpriſe warre againſt the good liking of the Senate? Moreover That litle help ſpoken of verſe 34. proceeded farre beyond the tyrannie of Antiochus whom Iudas Macabeus and his other brethren did over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live. To what end therfore ſhould the Prophet, when he had farre paſſed thoſe broyles, come ſayling back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine that waie he had formerly overpaſſed with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine inextricable confounding of thinges? Finally ſhall we think or imagine, that the Iewes calamities did ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in Antiochus alone, as that it ſhould be altogether needles to ſpeak a word of their conſequent troubles afterward? Neither doe theſe wordes anie better agree to his ſonnes, who never did atteine unto the greatneſſe of their Father. The Kingdome of Syria did more and more decaie, until at length not long after it was utterly waſted. This King therefore is not Antiochus, but ſome other farre ſurmounting him, one of thoſe foure cheife ones ſpoken of before ch. 7.17. and therfore the prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed article hath his emphaſis or expreſſe force of ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, diſtinguiſhing him from Antiochus, of whom he ſpoke in the wordes next and immediately going before, who was but ſmal and meane in compariſon of theſe foure cheife, and this King is the laſt of theſe foure: for the Lion, the Kingdome of the Aſſyrians, was aboliſhed and gone before this v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſion was ſhewed to Daniel, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ch. 10.1. Of the beare and leopard, the Perſians and the Grecians, there hath bene enough ſpoken in the former part of this chap. The terrible beaſt then onely remaineth, that variable wylde beaſt and of manie faſhions, which is this Kinge. For it is neceſſarie that the expoſition (of which kinde this laſt propheſie is) ſhould bring no new matter, as farre as it concerneth the generall heads, nor anie whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t depart from the generall type. By which it is alſo manifeſt that the fourth beaſt ch. 7. is not the Kingdome of the Seleucidans and Lagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dans,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17593:8"/> as ſome learned men have thought, ſeing this Kinge, that very beaſt, neither is Antiochus nor anie part of the Grecian Monarchie, which had no ſucceſſour after Antiochus greater then hee. But of this matter more heerafter. So as by thoſe neceſſarie arguments thus laid down, we are ledde by the hand to the Romanes, who tooke the lampe from the Grecians, and whom the Iewes afterward found and felt the muſt cruel revengers of their wickednes. For it is the intent of the ſpirit in a breife Synopſis or abridgement to our view, to deliver what the eſtate of the Iewes ſhould be, not onely to the firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt, which yet notwithſtandinge An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus never atteined to, but alſo to all ages ſucceding, till at lenght they ſhal bee gathered into one fould, &amp; be made together with us Citizens of the ſame Kingdome.</p>
                  <p>Other prophecies have made this manifeſt unto us &amp; the ſingular agreeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this prophecie will marveilouſly confirme the ſame. The Angel doth note or ſignifie, the Romane Monarchie by the name of one kinge, as if it were of ſome ſingular perſon after his manner; and then he addeth certaine properties, by which as in a glaſſe wee may behould his lively face. Firſt of all ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, where ſhall we finde a greater power to doe what hee liſt then in this empire? eſpecially from ſuch time as Antiochus the great by their meanes was deprived of all commande beyond the mountaine Taurus, and was commanded to conteine himſelf within the narrowe bonndes of Syria. For a litle before having van quiſhed Hanibal and triumphed over Perſeus the Macedonian, &amp; having ſlaine the Cymbrians or Danes, and all feare laid aſide farre and wyde round about, what ſhould reſtreine ſuch an extreame licentiouſnes of all things, and ſuch an unbridled appetite both of covetinge anie thinge, and of obteininge anie thing he coveted according to his will. The bridle of feare was caſt upon all other Kinges:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17593:8"/> onely the Romanes, whoſe power exceeded, did bite the bridle, &amp; would not be curbed by thoſe whom they had overcome in battell. Ptolomie felt of their tyrannicall power, whoſe Iſland Cyprus, although he were a kinge and their fellow and confederate, was proſcribed and ranſackt, not for anie offence and injurie, but onely for their deſire to enjoye ſo great a wealth, wherwith the Iſland was reported to abound. And whereas no fitt nor feigned coulour could be pretended, then Cato that great patrone of Iuſtice, as he was called, was made a publick robber of the wealth ſo ungodly coveted, that ſo, as I think, the groſſe diſhoneſtie of the facte might in ſome ſort be hid and concealed by the authoritie of the man. The Egiptian could not brook the wronge, but at the report of the matter poyſoned himſelf, Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus lib. 3. ch. 9.</p>
                  <p>The warre againſt Creete if we will take knowledge of the truth, we alſo made, ſaith the ſame Florus, onely through a deſire to vanquish that noble Iſland. But this licentiouſnes was nothing to the outragiouſnes of the Emperours. It would be over tedious to enter in the particulars, neither is it needfull in a matter ſo well knowne to all. Aſſuredly that which Daniel once ſpake of Nebucadnezar, agreeth very fitly to this Kinge, and for the Majeſtie that God gave him, all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, people, and languages trembled, &amp; feared before him; he put to death whom hee would, he ſmote whom he woulde, whom he would he ſett up, whom he woulde hee put downe Dan. 5.19. Theſe are the large boundes of an unlimited deſire proper to ſupreme authority. Let us not ſeek for them either in Antiochus, or in anie other ſervile prince, but onely in the higheſt empire. This is therefore his firſt marke, His unlimited power out of all controule. His pride foloweth, hee ſhall exalt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe &amp; magnifie himſelfe above all that is called God.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17593:9"/> Interpreters do uſe to carry theſe wordes to the impietie of this Kinge, which indeed is noted in the next wordes And hee ſhall ſpeak marveilous thinges, and wordes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the God of Gods. Thoſe former wordes therefore doe belonge to men: for pride is here ſett out by a twofold ſubject about the which it is exerciſed, partly men whom it contemneth and deſpiſeth as their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; partly God himſelf, of whom it doth both think and ſpeake unreverently. We know that men placed in higher degrees of dignitie, are in manie places in the Scripture called Gods, eſpecially ſuch as have anie government and commaund of thinges: this King ſhould make no accounte of all theſe in compariſon of himſelf, as it is evident in the people of Rome. For how ſhould not hee lift up himſelf above all, whom all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt through the whole worlde, hee held as his vaſſals and coppy-holders: who could obteine a Kingdome but by the helpe of his authoritie? or who could keepe one but with his goodwill? The Ptolemies Kings do flie to him as to the beſtower of Kingedomes, that Antiochus at his commaund might he made to lay downe his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious weapons, and depart out of Egypt which hee had ſubdued, and ſo to let goe his ſweet morſell out of his mouth againe: And without delay commeth Popilins flying into Egypt, and ſhowed by his doings how litle a legate of Rome did eſteem of anie kinge, he ſcornfully refuſeth the hand and embracements, hee bids leave-off his complements and friendlie ſalutations and making a circle, ſtrictly enioynes him a ſpeedie anſwere before he went out of that ſpace. Neither durſt the great King mutter a word againſt it, but remembring he had to doe with his Lord and Maiſter, quietly ſuffred hee the prey to be taken from him, and giving warning for the readines of al his carriage he departed out of Egypt. This Epimanes did more wiſely then Perſeus
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17593:9"/> the Macedonian, who wageing battaile with the Romane, learned at the le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to his great da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage by folowing the triumphing chariot of Aemilius, what a dangerous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it was to contend or fight with a ſuperiour, or one more then his match. Fooliſhly alſo did Gentius King of Illiricum, who would not ſubmitt to this tyrannicall prince before he was ſent priſoner to Rome together with his wife and children and kinsfolks by Ammius the Pretor. O Romane thou waſt indeed above every God, all Kings did ſubmitt their necks and yeeld under thy yoke Pruſias therfore the King of Bythinia, though not according to princelie dignitie, yet very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modiouſly, to make ſhew of the Romane eminencye, commanded his ſonne Nicomedes as an orphan or ward to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and acknowledged himſelf a free man of the people of Rome.</p>
                  <p>But we are to obſerue notwithſtanding that this King ſhould exalt and magnifie himſelfe by wreſting principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie by force and armes, and not by voluntarie ſubjection to him. Pruſias indeed willingly ſeemed to profeſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf their ſervant, but his profeſſion was but a baſe flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, which feare extorted, but he did not ingenuouſly nor willingly deſire it. What ſhould I make mention of Eumenes King of Pergamus, of Ariarathes King of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padocia, of Mithidathes King of Pontus, of Diatarus King of Salatia, who all of them and all others in all places ſubmitted themſelves to this King, either of their owne accorde or of compulſion. We ſee therfore that this agreeth to the Romane alone to whoſe will and pleaſure all other did reforme. Antiochus neither durſt nor was able to arrogate anie ſuch matter. But if wee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprete theſe Gods to bee the celeſtiall and divine powers, then is there leſſe likelihood in it, that hee ſhould preferre himſelfe before the heavenlie, which knew ſo wel he had a maiſter on earth. But theſe Gods heere
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17593:10"/> ſpoken of are not heavenlie but earthlie ones: That even as Antichriſt, who was afterward to ſucceed in this very ſeate, ſhould exalt himſelfe above all that is called God or is worſhipped, 2. Theſ. 2.4. by aſſuming to himſelfe a dominion over all the kings of the earth: ſo this king here ſhould goe before him in the ſame ſteppes, to make to his heire the more eaſie path and paſſage to the top of his axecrable pride to be abhorred of all men: ſuch is his arrogant haughtineſſe over men, but hee will not be conteyned within theſe boundes: hee wil uſe reproachfull wordes againſt the God of Gods, ſaith the text, But ſo did the Aſſyrian king alſo of olde, Hath anie of the Gods of the nations delivered his Land out of the hands of the King of Aſhur. 2. King. 18.33. And it is ſaid of Antiochus alſo, that hee ſlue manie men and ſpake very proudly. 1. Maca. 1, 25. This therfore ſeemeth to be a common note of great ſoveraigntie, which uſually breakes out into great blaſphemie againſt God himſelfe: yet there is reaſon in this place, wherfore it ſhould be proper and peculiar to the Romane, for the Aſſytian hath no part at all in this viſion, neither can it be referred to Antiochus, whoſe horrible miſchiefes are formerly recorded, that he ſhould pollute the holie place or ſanctuarie, and ſhould take awaie the daily ſacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fice, and ſet up the abominable deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation verſe 31. He had now alreadie paſſed and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded beyond thoſe wordes, why ſhould he now be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooved for inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderate end uncivill language after ſuch heynous miſcheifes? we doe not uſe to accuſe a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom we have prooved to have thruſt his neighbour through wit a ſword and after to laye to his charge that he prickt him with a pin or a needle alſo. This therfore is not Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochus his blaſphemie but the Romanes, who though they came behind him in wicked deedes againſt the God of Gods, yet they refrained not themſelves from wicked wordes. Although it bee not neceſſarie that theſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17593:10"/> wordes ſhould bee of the mouth, when as the foole hath ſaid in his heart there is no God: and it is certaine al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they uſed no wordes, and brake not out into termes, yet the Romanes after they grewe into acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the nation of the Iewes, did in their private thoughtes attribute more to their Iupiter of the capitoll, then to the great creatour of the worlde. But yet words are not wantinge, which are as witneſſes of notorious blaſphemie. Cicero, with the applauſe and approbation of his nation, doth not vouchſafe the true and ſincere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of God anie other name then a barbarous ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; neither ſo contented, his ungracious tongue goeth forward in determining thoſe ſacred things of divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution to bee both unworthie of the nobleneſſe and ſplendor of the Romane Empire, the gravitie and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their name, the inſtitutions of their anceſtours, and alſo to be odious and hatefull to the immortall Gods, becauſe the nation whoſe they were, was vanquiſhed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooved, preſecuted: for ſo hee playeth and maketh a flouriſh and oſtentation of his eloquence againſt the God of heaven in his oration for Flaccus.</p>
                  <p>That was but a light matter that Auguſtus commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his nephew Caius for contemning the religion of the Iewes. Tiberius did perſecute them with ſo greate hatred, that hee compelled all their worſhippers or Louers to burne all their holy garments with all their furniture; who alſo appointed and diſtributed the Iewes youth by a kind of oath, into the provinces of a corrupt ayre, and hee baniſhed the reſt of that nation &amp; their followers under a penaltie of perpetuall ſlaverie &amp; ſervitude, if they were not obedient, as Suetonius in his Tiberius witneſſeth ca: 36. yet notwithſtanding he would afterward have had Chriſt regiſtred among the Gods, if the authoritie of the Senate had not hindred it, whoſo auncient decree it was, that no God ſhould be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated by the Emperor, unleſſe it were approved by the Senate.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17593:11"/> O the notorious blaſphemie of this King, with whom the divinitie is weighed and eſteemed according to mans arbitrement and judgment, except God doe pleaſe men, hee ſhal not be God: man muſt now be propitious and favourable to God as Tertullian ſpeaketh in his Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geticus.</p>
                  <p>Verie great proſperitie goeth with their intolerable pride, which hath bene in no kingdome greater then heere. With what proſperous enterpriſes from the firſt foundations hath every thing bene begunne, continued and perfected? One warre hath alwaies drawne on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and new occaſions did incontinently followe ech other, ſo commodious, fit and ſeaſonable, as that the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane armies might ſeeme not ſo much to have ſought principalitie as to be called therunto.</p>
                  <p>Vpon juſte cauſe did Servius Tullius one of the firſt Kinges ſeeme to have familiar compaine with Fortune, which proſperitie was no whit leſſened in ſucceeding ages and generations. thoſe eſpecially after the ſubduing of Syria: whence it came that Rome had ſo manie eminent, renowmed and ſtately temples of fortune, but none of wiſdome, temperance, patience, fortitude and magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitie: doubtles the Romane people did more increaſe by fortune,<note place="margin">Ceſars motto was, Veni, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, vici.</note> then by proweſſe. Surely that title or motto of theire wordes, which Ceaſar in his pompous pageant, bare before him in his triumph of Pontus, I came, I ſaw, I overcame, might have bene common to the whole empire.</p>
                  <p>Plutarch his litle book of the fortune of the Romanes, may afoard an ample and large diſcourſe of this their feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie to him that deſireth more. But leaſt anie weake minde ſhould be too much diſcouraged with theſe their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous affaires, there is added a comfort of an appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſet time. Till he hath accompliſhed his wrath, ſaith he, what wrath? not his owne, which cannot be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17593:11"/> ſatisfyed, but Gods, who was angrie for the ſinnes of the people, who ordeineth the tyrants for judgement, &amp; eſtabliſheth the ſpoylers for correction Hab. 1.12. The reaſon which followeth is doubtfull, for it maie be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: bicauſe ſeueritie is to be exerciſed: and ſo it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth unto the Iewes, as if it were determined with God to correcte and puniſh the refractarie, by giving to this Kinge, the people of Rome a great ſovereigntie, as the Apoſtle interpreteth a like place in Iſaie, for that which the Prophet ſaith, The conſumption decreed ſhal flow with righteouſnes, for the Lord God of hoaſts ſhal make the conſumption &amp; deciſion in the midſt of the Land. ch. 10.22. Paul rendreth it, For he wil make his account &amp; gather it into a ſhort ſumme with righteouſnes: for the Lord will make a ſhort worde and count in the earth Rom. 8.29. by which teſtimonie he prooveth that the Iewes are to be rejected and but a few of that nation to be ſaved, which ſeveritie be afterward calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Rom. 11.22 by a word anſwering to the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> deciſion. The Grecians turne this place of Iſaie. It is brought to an end and perfection with haſt, in the very ſame with Paul, His ſhort work, for the thinge determined doth come to his end with a kinde of haſtening.</p>
                  <p>The other interpretation concerneth the Romanes themſelves becauſe the determination is made, that is to ſay, the boundes are ſet &amp; fixed, beyond which, the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the wicked King ſhal not paſſe, whom the bridle of divine providence ſhall moderate even in the leaſt and ſmalleſt mattrers; for that doth deciſion or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination ſignifie, which doth not conſider the matter in ſumme and generall, but ſeverally by every member diſtributed into his parts: a matter of ſingular comfort againſt diſtruſt, as though God did not by his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence reach over particular matters: both meanings are
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17593:12"/> very good, but which is the more apt and fit in this place let the reader judge.</p>
                  <p n="37">37. <hi>Neither ſhall he regard the God of his fathers.</hi> Now he informeth us what maner of one this King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhould be towards his owne, wherunto he propoundeth a threefold proprietie, The contempt of his fathers Gods, No regard to the deſire of women, and the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying of himſelfe above all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what is therfore that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte of the Goddes? Interpreters doe referre it to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regard of all Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which yet notwithſtanding the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans we knowe, have too ſuperſtitiouſly obſerved, as is evide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to bee ſeene by manie examples &amp; in Valerius Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximus lib. 1.1. Neither ſhall we fynde their poſteritie anie whit to relinquiſh the inſtitutions of their Aunceſtours in this matter. Their Children after the Grecian Monarchie went on in the ſame Courſe of ſuperſtition, wherin their auncient fathers had gone before them: Theſe things therfore doe rather belong to Civill policie, which this new King ſhould innovate and bring in, altogether dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feringe from that which his aunceſtours had obſerved. For the civill Magiſtrate is called God, as we ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and therfore his not regardinge the Gods of his fathers is nothing elſe, but his light eſteme of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, which his fathers uſed in times paſt: and not long after the Romanes had ſubdued Iudea, the government of this people became a Monarchie, which was before an Ariſtocratie or at leaſt mixt of the people and the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. Their firſt government of olde in former ages was by Kinges, but they were at length expelled, and the name grew ſo odions as that Tarquinius the Conſull could no longer be tolerated, becauſe be affected the name of a King. And from thence forward the ſame ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was derived to all their poſteritie as manie examples doe make manifeſt, and that decree of the Senate, wherin there was order taken that no Kinges ſhould enter into the Citie.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:17593:12"/>
                  <p>But it was fatall and ominous at that time to be ſo baſie about excluding of Kinges, when by and by after a king was to riſe up amongſt themſelves. In the time of Cicero the ſoothſayer or interpreter of the Sibills, earneſtly contended in the Senate, that he whom they accounted as a Kinge ſhould be alſo called a Kinge, if they would liue in ſafetie.</p>
                  <p>But this was taken in very ill part, in ſo much that the Oratour adviſeth them to deale firſt with their great ones, that they would bring forth anie thing out of the Sibils prophecies rather then a Kinge, whom neither Gods nor men would ſuffer anie longer at Rome. But thy prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtication fayled thee, O thou wittie Oratour. Thou ſaweſt with thine eies a litle after a King at Rome which thou didſt prophecie ſhould never come to paſſe. This contempt therfore of their fathers Gods is a new ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Emperous violating the law of their fathers, and bringing thoſe Magiſtrates into ſubjection, who were wont in their old Fathers time to have the cheife com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund. This chaunge of government was a remarkeable note for all men eaſily to diſtinguiſh between this King and others. And ſo doth Daniel admirably conſent with Iohns revelation, what time as Iohn did write theſe thinges, he telleth us five Kinges were fallen and the ſixt did then flouriſh. Daniel in theſe wordes doth as it were foretel the funerall of the fift Kinge,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.10.</note> and the birth or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitie of the ſixt, which ſhould aſpire to the top and higheſt commaund, by the contempte of the auncient Gods, the old Magiſtrats to whom their fathers yeelded all obedience. As concerning the deſire of women, there is no leſſe difficultie about the righte meaninge. The interpreters take it paſſively for that deſire which men beare towards women, wherby it commeth to paſſe that ſome referre it to luſt, others to humanitie and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſie, but the like conſtruction is active elſwhere, as the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17593:13"/> deſire of all nations, that is to ſay, which all nations doe deſire, Hag. 2.8. So the deſire of women, is that which women doe deſire, which were very unequall and unfitte to referre unto luſt. What is it then that women doe moſt of all deſire and affect? To have their children moſt honourable. Bathſheba ſeemeth heerupon to requeſt an oath of David, that her Sonne, if ſhe had one by him, ſhould ſucceed him in the Kingdome, which happily ſhe wreſted from him before ſhee did yeelde unto his luſt. Aſſuredly, The deſire of women brought the mother of Zebedeus children to ſhewe her outragious ambition in aſking the cheife ſeates in Chriſts kingdome for her two ſonnes. Wherfore this kinge ſhould have no regard to this deſire, becauſe he would be nothinge carefull for his naturall ſucceſſion, otherwiſe then in all other king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. For if we caſt our eves vpon anie other govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; what doe the fathers more earneſtly, being kings, affect, then to leave their children, a quiet, ſtable and ſtedfaſt kingdome? But this care nothinge troubleth this kinge Octavius therfore ſucceedeth I. Ceaſar, Tiberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us his ſonne in lawe Octavius; Caligula Tyberius and ſo afterward: yea for the moſt part in degrees much further of, the ſucceſſour no way allyed vnto him that we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before eſpecially, when as the higheſt empire was at the pleaſure or at the beſtowing of fierce and Cruel ſoldiers, not of the Senate gathered together of lawfull aſſemblies. Sometimes indeed in ſucceeding ages one or two ſonnes now and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> have enioyed their fathers kingdome by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritaunce, but that was rather by the choice and affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſoldiers, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the advice of their fathers, who percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving how greatly force and violence had prevayled did not mind the care of ſucceſſion, which they ſaw to be in other mens power. Such therfore ſhould the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment bee, as ſhould more reſpect the honouring of all eſtates with great authoritie, then the deſire of women to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17593:13"/> inrich or ennoble their Sonnes with anie ſingular prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence above the reſt, and it were indeed a marveilous matter if the wiſedome of God had not forewarned us of it longe before, that the emperours having the cheife commaund of all matters, there ſhould be ſo few found in ſo great a number to have their lawfull iſſue to ſucceed them.</p>
                  <p>This is therfore the ſecond, cleare, famous, and dom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall note, wherby this empire ſhould be knowne. The third is his magnifiing himſelfe above all; where there commeth againe a new contempte of the Gods, nor Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard anie God ſaith he. To what purpoſe is this? was not this impietie ſufficiently reprooved before in the former verſe? He wil magnifie himſelfe above all Gods, and now alſo in the beginning of this, and he ſhall not regard the God of his fathers. This repetition is not in vayne, but a new degree of the like pride. The contempt of the Gods in the former verſe was of all forreine Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates amonge all nations whatſoever. The contempt of the Gods in the beginning of this verſe, was of their owne domeſticall but auncient and inſtituted of old. The contempt of the Gods in this place is of the preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, Pretours and Tribunes, and the reſt now in being, whoſe names as yet remayned, but all the power and authoritie was inveſted in this cheife Magiſtrate alone. Tacitus in the firſt entraunce of his hiſtorie ſhewing how Auguſtus by litle and litle drew the right of all offices to himſelf alone: Firſt he ſet vpon the Conſulſhip like an enemie by force as Suetonius declareth in Auguſtus cap. 27. the reſt were offred him at his pleaſure: he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall Tribune or protectour of the Commons, and had perpetuall government alſo of lawes and manners.</p>
                  <p>Therfore the other Magiſtrates were but titular onely, and a vaine ſhew and ſemblaunce of authoritie, appointed onely to eaſe the Prince of trouble in their Kingdomes, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17593:14"/> not to exerciſe anie abſolute authoritie. No marvell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if he exalt himſelfe above all theſe, whom he vſed as his vaſſals and baſe flatterers. All Kinges in their terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories have cheife commaund, neither doe they reſpect anie other inferiour God or Magiſtrate, whom them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves created of their owne ſubjects, but on the contrary ſide are honoured of all men. But this eſpecially ſhould bee remarkable in this empire, becauſe the beginning of innovations are moſt of all obſerved, we finde therfore this third note moſt conſpicuous and manifeſt in this Kinge, which is not at all obſerved in others by reaſon of long cuſtome.</p>
                  <p n="38">38. <hi>But in his place ſhall he honour the God of forces.</hi> Hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to have bene more common notes, now he ſetteth vpon more ſpeciall ones, and more proper to certaine places, and firſt of all how he ſhould behave himſelfe towards the true God. For the better vnderſtanding wherof the wordes are firſt to be diſcuſſed, which are diverſly ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by interpreters.</p>
                  <p>The learned Tremelius and Iunius doe tranſlate them abſolutely: And as concerning the God of great ſtrength he ſhall honour him in his place, I ſay, He ſhal honour the God which his fathers knew not &amp;c. but this conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth require a nominative caſe, <hi>this God of forces,</hi> &amp;c. as Pſ. 11.4. &amp; 18.31. Apoca. 2.26. &amp; 3.12.21. as we have there obſerved vpon the place. In ſuch like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions the prepoſition is wanting indeed, but the want therof is ſo frequent in this kinde, that I think it is no where fully expreſſed. Moreover this tranſlation doth give the whole honour to the God whom his fathers knew not, wheras yet the Angel expreſſly leaveth ſome honour to the God of forces: for thoſe wordes. (He ſhall honour the God) in the former part of the verſe, muſt have the like ſignification with the ſame wordes in the ſecond part therof. Furthermore except the words
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17593:14"/> (He ſhall honour) were to be joyned with thoſe in the beginning of the verſe the God of forces, the accent ath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nach in <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall honour ſhould be altogether in vayne, and the compulation of the next word, yea and alſo the whole word (God) next repeated.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond word (Mauzim, of forces) hath no leſſe difficultie. The ſignification is agreed vpon, but the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of it is divers waies applied. Some doe reteine the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew word it ſelf, and think it added to ſignifie an Idol, and that in very deed not unprobably: for he that a litle before was called a contemner of the Gods, how ſhall hee preſently in the next wordes be accounted a worſhipper of the true God? But if I be not deceived, the hiſtorye will remove this block, and refute the interpretation. Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melius doth expound it of the true God, whoſe judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I approove of, for ſo is the word taken before in v. 31. and by and by againe in v. 39. eſpecially being ioyned with mibiſaijm <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which word is alſo ſpoken of the holie place in verſ. 24. Thirdly <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> gnalcanno, vpon his place, or in his place, to wit, of this Kinge, as learned Calvin doth expound it: as if this Kinge wold acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no other God but ſuch as ſhould be faſtened to his place, ſhoulde come after the word jecabed, he ſhall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: which being otherwiſe, it cannot, as I think, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to anie thing elſe, but to that which went before, namely, to the true God in whoſe place this honour was to be done.</p>
                  <p>The double ſenſe therfore of the wordes evinceth that the true God of great ſtrength is to be honoured in his owne place by this Kinge; which to be done, the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie alſo beareth witneſſe. For Pompey havinge ſurprized Ieruſalem and entred the temple, when as within it the table and candleſtick, and the cuppes were all of gold, and great abundaunce of ſweet incenſe, and beſide about two thouſand talents of ſacred monies in the treaſurie,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17593:15"/> yet made conſcience of touching anie thing at all, but heerin alſo was like himſelfe and did nothing vnworthie of his other vertues. Ioſephus in lib. 14. of Antiquities and cha. 8. He did not indeed forſake his old idolatries, neither did he acknowledge the true God by repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taunce, but yet he caried him ſelfe more temperately and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately then the wicked Antiochus had formerly done. In reſpect of whoſe outragiouſnes, was not this admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble abſtinence, great pietie and reverence towards God? But over and beſides the next day folowing he commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the keepers of the temple to purge it, to have the ſacrifices appointed by the lawe reſtored againe, and gave the preiſthood to whom it was due.</p>
                  <p>There is added to this humanitie, which is honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the true God, the decrees of Caeſar and of the enſuing Emperours for libertie graunted to the Iewes to live after their owne lawes, as Ioſephus hath it in his 14. book of Antiquities in his ſixteenth and ſeventeenth chapters.</p>
                  <p>The true God is greatly honoured, when libertie is graunted to his people to worſhip him according to his owne appointment. And although the Romane Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents did make their reſidence at Ieruſalem yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they diminiſhed nothing of that graunte. Iuſtly therfore maie this Kinge be ſaid to honour the God of forces in this place, whoſe deputies for the preſent did preſerve the libertie of the holie people to liue after their owne lawe. This is then a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall note wherby this King is diſtinguiſht from all others. Manie have brought Ieruſalem, into their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection at ſundrie times, but none of them all have go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned the Citie by Preſidents, and in the mean time graunted the Iewes to enjoy their owne religion and worſhip.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:17593:15"/>
                  <p>But althoug this honour be of ſome certaine place, it is yet but generally propounded the diſtinct and ſeverall kindes therof are declared in that which foloweth: And the God, ſaith he, Whom his fathers knew not, ſhal he honour with golde &amp;c. what God is this? A forged one indeed, as ſome have thought, who referre theſe thinges to Antiochus Epiphanes, who ſet up Iupiter Olympius in the temple. But we have ſhewed already that theſe things can no waies agree to Antiochus. And how could Iupiter Olympius be unknowne to his aunceſtours, whom theſe fathers eſpecially, worſhipped? The Gentiles knew well enough the whole rout of Gods, but the onely true Iehovah, when both they &amp; their fathers were igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of this God; whom alone it concerned them to knowe after the Romanes had to doe with the Iewes, they got ſomthing of him by hearing. Whence it is that we read of ſome holie centurious in the Goſpell, who in the time of their governements in Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ea, have learned and atteyned the ſaving knowledge of God.</p>
                  <p>This is therfore the ſame true God which was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly called the God of forces, who could ſcarce be better perceived then by that groſſe and palpable igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance wherin the nations of old did formerly wallowe.</p>
                  <p>How then did this King conferre to the honour of this God, gold, ſilver and precious ſtones? Doubtles by a noble and coſtly repayring of the temple; for in the reigne of Auguſtus the temple of Ieruſalem was repaired, and reſtored, towards the which building what a huge maſſe of Gold, ſilver and precious ſtones, and other very coſtly things was layd out? A thouſand cariages were imployd in carying of ſtones, ten thouſand of the moſt ſkilfull artificers, and moreouer a thouſand preiſts who ſhould ſee to the framing of the inmoſt porches, from
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17593:16"/> whence all the prophane and uncleane were debarred, neither was the building finiſhed in leſſe time then eight yeeres. Hence therfore maie a man more eaſily gueſſe then give in a juſt account of ſuch an infinite charges: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if he call to minde the goodly golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vyneyards, and the other ornaments of ſuch an admirable work both mannels and materials ſo coſtly: Ioſephus Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities book. 15. 14. c. 14. Now then did God performe that which of old, he had foretold by his Prophet Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai 2.8.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.8.</note> The ſilver is mine and the gold is mine, ſaith the Lord of hoſtes. Some of the Iewes that returned after the captivitie, which had ſeene the former houſe are ſaid to weep with a lowde voyce when the foundation was layde. Ezra. 3.12. But Haggai biddeth them be of good courage, for the glorie of the ſecond houſe ſhal be greater then the firſt and the deſire of all nations ſhall come unto it, yea whatſoever the ſecond houſe in the building be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun was wanting of in ſplendour and magnificent ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, God promiſeth to ſupplie, whoſe is all the gold and ſilver which accordingly he plentifully poureth out for the furniſhing and ornaments of the houſe. And now at this time they did religioſly and earneſtly endevour to bewtifie the Temple, to prepare it for our Lords com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge, who was ſhortly to come unto his owne houſe.</p>
                  <p>For ſoone after the temple was finiſhed our Lord Ieſus Chriſt was borne, who was greater then Salomons temple, for whom the houſe was worthily prepared, being ſo ſumptuoſly bewtified and adorned, as in token of that moſt glorious temple, which himſelfe was ſoone after to finiſh and make perfect, which was alſo ſhewed in ſome ſort to be cheifly amongſt the gentiles, ſeing they were now the cheife authours of the typicall ones re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoringe, for this ſeemeth to be no ſleight preſage of the ſpirituall buildinge into the which they were ſhortly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17593:16"/> after to be brought and choſen, by that high and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute workman.</p>
                  <p>Thus ſhall he doe in the moſt ſtronge holdes with a ſtrange God.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>verſ.</hi> 39</note> He doth further proceed to make this king better knowne by other of his doinges: for theſe wordes are an anſwere to a ſecret objection wherby thoſe thinges formerly of the temples building, may ſeeme litle to agree with and to the Romanes: for we know that Herod be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed all that coſt of his owne. The Angel therfore meeteth with it, as if he ſhould ſay, I would not have you to think me to avouch, that the Romanes did or would undertake anie thing with their owne handes, coſt or meanes, but whatſoever he did in the holdes of the ſtrong God, be did it all at the charge and trauel of a ſtrange God, that is to ſaie, of a certaine inferiour ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, which held his place rather by force and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie then by anie lawfull authoritie, whence he ſhall worthily be iudged a ſtranger, or ſtrange God. And who can be ignorant that Herod was ſuch a one, an Edomite by birth and a ſtranger, who had no right at all of lawfull authoritie over the Iewes? Wherfore the Romanes ſhould doe all by his meanes, which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on the houldes of the ſtrong God: that is to ſay, which they beſtowed upon the reſtoring of the Temple: for theſe are the holdes of the God of forces, whence hee privily ſendeth ſuccour to his owne people, and yeeldeth help unto them in adverſitie, as the frequent and fervent prayers of the ſaincts doe manifeſt, wherby they labour all they can, that God would heart and helpe out of his temple Pſ. 18.7. to which purpoſe alſo is that of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Amos 1.2. The Lord roareth out of Sion and uttereth his voice from Ieruſalem. And it is manifeſt whatſoever was done in the building of the Temple, it was done by the authoritie of the Romane Emperour, but yet by the coſt and travel of Herod, a ſtrange God;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17593:17"/> that doth Herod himſelf acknowledge in an oration to the people concerning that matter.</p>
                  <p>Amongſt other opportunities and meanes of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing ſo great a work, which was a terrour to manie mens mindes, he rekoneth the friendſhip of the Romans by the benefit wherof he ſpecially truſteth he ſhal be able and fitting to bring all the perfection which he had purpoſed and propounded to himſelf. Now ſaith he, ſeing by Gods providence I obteine a Kingdome and have leiſure, ready monie and great revenues comming in &amp; that which is moſt of all, the friendſhip of the Romans, the Lords of the world. I will doe my endevour &amp;c. Ioſep. Antiq. li. 15.14. See how he attributeth the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of his meanes to the friendſhip of the Romanes, wherof hee made more accounte then of his leaſure or ready monie at will, which yet he more evidently decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, when as after the work finiſhed, he did dedicate a golden eagle of great waight upon the great dore of the temple, the armes of that King, by whoſe favour and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, that ſtrange God had ſhewed himſelf ſo bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full upon the holdes of the Almightie God. And hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto of his works towards God. Now in ſpeciall what manner of one he ſhould be towards men, Whom, ſaith he<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he ſhal aknowledge, he ſhal increaſe with glory, for all authoritie was in the handes of the Romanes from the firſt touch at that province. He by his legate Scaurus did preferre Ariſtobulus the younger brother both to the preieſthood and the Kingdome. He alſo by Pompey re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rcanus againe, he made Antipater the Edomite the governour of all Iudea, and appointed his ſonnes Phaſaelus and Herod to raigne, who but he confirmed Herods will and teſtament, and declared not Archilaus his ſonne for king, but graunting him a moytie of Herods jurisdiction, made him a ruler of the people?</p>
                  <p>That which of late belonged to one now by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17593:17"/> of this King, who might doe whatſoever him liſted, was divided amonge fowre, Philip and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas and Salome doe enioy equall portions with Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus. Ioſeph. Antiq. lib. 17. c. 13. ſo he devided the land for money and the hiſtorie makes it manifeſt, that this King made more account of talents then of reaſon and honeſtie, juſtice and equitie, whoſoever brought the greateſt weight of gold did ſpeed beſt in his ſuite. But that buying and ſelling is of all other the moſt memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, when after the overthrow of Ieruſalem Veſpaſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Titus emperours had famouſly triumphed, Caeſar writes from Rome to Liberius Maximus, appointed governour, to make ſale of all the land of the Iewes: Ioſep: of the Iewes warre. lib. 7. c. 26. Hiher without doubt had the angel reſpect, giving us this for an infallible mark of this kinge, that no place may be left anie more to doubt of his perſon.</p>
                  <q>And at the time of the end ſhall the King of the ſouth puſh at him.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>verſ.</hi> 40.</note>
                  </q>
                  <p>Hitherto have we ſpoken of the firſt of the three op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſours as wee did diſtinguiſh them in the Analyſis or Reſolution. The ſecond and third doe folowe, the prophecie is but ſhort in the ſecond, very large in the third, becauſe it did more concerne the Saincts to be very well fortified againſt his tyrannie, as we ſhall ſee in the expoſition. Our learned Broughton doth ſeperate thoſe wordes from the former with a prefixed title, for the argument in a differing character to this purpoſe. The third expedition of Antiochus into Egypt againſt Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomeus Philometor. But we ſhewed in the 36. verſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that there was no ſuch third expedition, which is grounded upon a wrong interpretation of the 29 verſe of this chapter, neither is it confirmed by the conſent of anie hiſtorie: alſo theſe wordes are flatte againſt it: for the King of the South ſhal provoke this Kinge and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17593:18"/> fall upon him with his ſpightfull hornes: but the King of Eygpt attempted nothing at all againſt Antiochus from the time of his departure out of his country at the commaundement of the Romane legate. The Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies thought themſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lves happie men to be delivered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch a grievous enimie by the royall authoritie of the Romanes, ſo farre they were from provoking him to battaile. Beſides, this conflict ſhould be at the end of the Kinge: but Antiochus toward his end had all his warre againſt the Eymaitans or Perſians in the eaſt, not againſt Ptoleemie in the ſouth. In the hundred fortie &amp; third yeere of the Kingdome of the Greekes hee left E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt being therto compelled by the authoritie of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, at which time in his returne he grievouſly tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the Iewes, but two yeeres after he raged moſt cruelly, ſending Apollonius, to root out utterly the Iewiſh religion, if it were poſſible. At the beginning of the hundred fortie and ſeventh yeere, when he thought to break into Iudea, it ſodeinly came into his minde to commit this taſke to Lyſias, and himſelfe to go firſt into Perſia, from whence he never returned alive againe into Syria.</p>
                  <p>Shall wee thruſt up together ſo maine victories, and thoſe of ſo manie nations, which the angel attributeth to the King of the north, into ſuch narrow ſtreights of three yeeres and a few monthes more at the moſt, and in the meane time not think them worthie of one wordes cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration or praiſe, by the hiſtoriographers? Antiochus ſurely after the Romanes had reſtrayned him from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king warre where he liſted, and that he muſt of neceſſitie lay downe his weapons, ſeemeth to give himſelf over to that monſtrous ryot, which Atheneus deſcribeth in the wordes of Polybius. He had monie enough for that wondrous pompe, after he had robd the temple of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem of a thouſand eight hundred talents, in his returne
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17593:18"/> out of Egypt, wherwithall in the pride &amp; haughtineſſe of his heart he imagined, he could make the land navigable and the ſea paſſable on foote. 2. Macab. 5.21. And what elſe now ſhould ſuch a man doe, borne to no thriftines, but to wallow himſelfe in the myre &amp; puddle of his owne filthie pleaſures, who had an injunction for ceſſation of armes? And ſo Polib. in Athen. Dipnoſeph. li. 5. All theſe thinges, ſaith he, were brought to paſſe, partly by thoſe thinges which he had ſcraped together out of Egypt, after he had deceived the young king Philomether with a feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed league, &amp; partly by the help of his friendes, but he had pilled alſo very manie temples. But to make ſhort, All the noble acts which are herafter rehearſed of the king of the north, doe call us back to ſome other beſide Antioch: We are not to think that the Iewes calamities had an end in this one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie, or that they needed no other cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the enſuinge evils. The Angel ſweareth in the revelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that that ſhould be finiſhed which God had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed by his prophets in times paſt when the ſeventh An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel ſoundeth c. 10.7. &amp; this ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nd is the laſt period of time which ſhal put an end to all prophecies.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7.</note> But among the Prophets there is not anie one, to whom God hath impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at anie time more plentifull revelations, either of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger continaunce, or of more exact knowledge of all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular matters, then unto Daniel: neither is it likely that there ſhould be no remainder of comfort in the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies for the people of God, whom we know he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined at the length to joyne to his Church, when he hath gathered the remnants together. Theſe things doe I ſpeak to this end, becauſe I ſee other learned men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreine thoſe things which followe within the boundes of Chriſts incarnation, howſoever they confeſſe ingenuouſly and confime by arguments, that they can no waies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to Antiochus. But I trow it ſhall evidenly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peere to anie man embracing the truth without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, that it is the purpoſe of the ſpirit in this place
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17593:19"/> to compriſe in a ſhort abridgement the whole eſtate of the people of the Iewes in a continuall orderly ſucceſſion even to the ſecond comming of Chriſt. Let us come therfore to the wordes, The time of the end wherof mention is made in the firſt place, ſheweth manie middle matters to be overpaſſed, and that a paſſage is made to the laſt thinges; yet not to the laſt and vtter ruine of this King, the Romane Emperour, but to his ſliding glorie, and end of his vnbrideled power, wherby of late he did whatſoever he pleaſed. Neither did anie remarkable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident fall out beſides thoſe thinges already ſpoken of, after the defacing of the Citie and ſcattering of the nation by Adrian, which handled the remainders of this people in like maner as Veſpaſian, had their fathers not manie yeares before. Iuſtly therfore doth he paſſe with ſo ſwift a courſe from thoſe times to the weakened and decayed empire. A litle before the end therfore of the flouriſhing Romane empire, (the King of the ſouth) that is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racens ſhall encounter him, which with their Captaine Mahomet did firſt make an invaſion into the Romane Dominion out of Arabia and the ſoutherlie places neere adjoyninge.</p>
                  <p>The beginning of this hoſtile and violent aſſault was about the yeere ſix hundred and thirtie, which in ſhort time fel out ſo happily vnto them, that within leſſe then thirty yeeres they got from the Romane empire Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, all Syria, Africa and the greater Aſia. The Spirit doth fitly liken this nation to a beaſt that ſtriketh with his hornes jithbag,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> ſaith he, <hi>He</hi> ſhall puſh at him, he ſhall ſo wantonly and proudly inſult, neyther with ill ſucceſſe nor with leſſe force then the wilde beaſts uſe to doe, whoſe ſtrength is all in their hornes. Great was the inſolencie of the Agarens, who hearing that Conſtance the Emperour had prepared a navie againſt them, ſtaid not till he ſhould purſue and invade them, but preſently
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17593:19"/> came flyeing vpon him into Phenice in Lycia, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came him in a great battayle by ſea: <hi>Zonar. Conſtanſ.</hi> Afterward for ſeven years together they vexed his ſonne Conſtantinus Pogonatus, and in their great pride bent all their forces againſt the royall Citie, which they moſt eagerly aſſaulted as manie years almoſt as the Grecians did Troy of old, as ſcorning the leſſer townes and judging the miſtriſſe alone worthy, to the which they might intend their journey with earneſt deſire. But thou wilt ſaie then, If the Spirit would fall downe into theſe times, why doth he paſſe over the Goths, Vandals, Scythians and the other northerne, rude and barbarous people, by whoſe invaſions this Romane King was weakned and wearied before theſe Saracens fel vpon him.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe it was his purpoſe to touch thoſe oppreſſours onely, which ſhould be troubleſome to the people of the Iewes, which ſuffred no great loſſe by this waſting of Europe, moſt of them remaining in Africa and Aſia. In which places being free from the Romane yoake, they ſerved a new ſlaverie by ſubmitting themſelves to the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Agarens. So the holie land in times paſt, the Iewes countrie, fel vnder their dominion at length. The Spirit therfore maketh mention eſpecially of theſe by whom the Iewes were to ſuffer moſt hardſhip. Neither doth he in this place detect the Iewes by ſuch wordes as he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when he had to doe with Antiochus: for the legall worſhip being abrogate by the death of Chriſt, for which the Iewes to this day ſo eagerly ſtrive, it cannot be that they ſhould ſuffer anie thing for godlines ſake, for which cauſe the Spirit ſhould ſpeak of Religion oppreſſed, as it fel out vnder Antiochus, wherfore he vouchſafeth the Iewes no mention at all, onely he rehearſeth theſe enemies whom they ſhould finde hurtfull and grievous. Such is therfore the King of the ſouth. The King of the north is deſcribed at large by his preparation after the maner of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17593:20"/> a whirlewynd, and by his warlike inſtruments of all ſorts then by his happie progreſſe in this verſe.</p>
                  <p>But who is this King of the north? Not Antiochus, as we have before declared ſufficiently, though the ſame title of the King of the north be given to the Kinges of Syria. The other notes will not ſuffer it as the inſuing expoſition will manifeſt. Neither is it the Romane de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending himſelfe againſt the Agarens: for that (At the time of the end) did belong to the declining of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Empire, but the King of the north doth grow into great authoritie from this beginninge, as the words folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing doe ſhew: which reaſon alſo enforreth that this bickering muſt of neceſſitie be referred to ſome other time then that which went before the comming of our Lord Chriſt: for the Romane Kinges did as yet flouriſh and grow more and more, neither at that time had attei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to his height and maturitie. But this warre fel out about the end of the flouriſhing of the Empire. It is not then to bee doubted but that the King of the north is the Empire of the Turckes. We know that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts of the north did caſt out this baſe rabble into the world through the ſtraights of the Caſpian ſea, which at length looſing his reines for libertie, mightily aſſailed our continent on every ſide, and doth in theſe daies violently aſſault us as it were a whirlewinde. But who it is againſt whom the angell ſaith, He ſhall come againſt: the King of the ſouth or the Romane, it may be doubted of: As a whirle wind, ſaith he, ſhall he fall vpon him.</p>
                  <p>He vanquiſhed indeed the Empire of the Saracens in Aſia, but the weight and force of his tyrannie did lye eſpecially againſt the Romane whom the angel makeththe common butt to both Kinges, both of the north and ſouth, to pearce him through with their darts and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, as the hiſtory ſheweth evidently. Havinge ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17593:20"/> found out the adverſaries, let us ſee in the ſeverall parts how the deſcription will agree. He ſhall invade, ſaith he, a whirlwinde and tempeſt ſuddeinly, ſpeedily and mightily ſhaking and waſtinge all thinges, whoſe force can ſcarſely be anie way avoyded but by flight, which indeed agreeth to none more fitly and truly then to the turkiſh tyrannie from the yeare one thouſand three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, when he began vtterly to overthrow Cities, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, armies, layeng along and ſpoylinge all that come in his way.</p>
                  <p>The outragiouſnes of the Turks did as much exceed that of the Saracens, as a violent tempeſt ruſhing from above, exceedeth the fiercenes of a beaſt puſhnig with his horne. The violence of this beaſt may be avoyded by flight or reſiſtaunce, and our men have repreſſed at length the inſolencie of the Saracens, though with their great trouble and loſſe: but it is not in mans power to oppoſe the terriblenes and force of the whirlewindes, from which it is hard in anie corners or coverts to make an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape. Whence it came to paſſe that our warres have not ſo much put off the furie of the Turkes as provoked it: neither is anie better to be expected vntill his tyrannie be come to his appointed time. His warlike inſtruments are chariots, horſmen and ſhippes: the hooked iron cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots were in frequent uſe with the Auncients, as it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt both by ſacred and prophane hiſtorie: The Romanes firſt ſawe them in the warre of Antiochus, and after that againſt Mithridates: They ſtroke great terrour at the firſt, but afterward they were derided and ſcorned as Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getius ſheweth, book. 3.</p>
                  <p>Wherfore the Romanes never vſed theſe chariots, and while they bore the ſwaie and vanquiſhed, others alſo caſt them off as vnprofitable on every ſide: Here therfore he doth rather allude, to the auncient Cuſtome, then ſtrictly determine that the Kinge of the North would vſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17593:21"/> ſuch a kind of armes: vnles peradventure theſe chariots be wagons and other cariages appointed for the armies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moovals wherof the Turkes vſe abundaunce, though they have great plentie of camels. They may alſo be referred to thoſe great gunnes which are drawne vpon wheeles, which doe reſemble a kind of chariots, ſpitting fire. The Turkes abound in horſemen, they bring more of them into the warres then almoſt all the Chriſtian princes joyned together.</p>
                  <p>They have alſo very great navies well furniſhed at their pleaſures: for they were not contented with the boundes of Aſia, but providing ſhipping they ſailed into Europe with a deſire to ſubdue and conquere our world alſo. He wanteth then no kind of preparation, wherwithall the Angel ſaid he ſhould be furniſhed. The ſucceſſe is ſummarily ſignified in the laſt wordes: And he ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Countryes and ſhall overflow and paſſe over, that is, They ſhall goe vp on the bredthe of the earth, as Iohn ſpeaketh Rev. 20.9.</p>
                  <p>The firſt wordes therof doe ſhewe the largenes of his tyrannie, for it ſhal not be conteined within the boundes of one Countrie, but he ſhall ſpread himſelfe into manie regions, The next wordes ſhew his eaſie victories, which ſhalbee as ſoone and as eaſily gotten, as a low ground is ſoone covered with an overflowinge of waters. The third ſheweth the ſafetie of his victories wherby he may freely goe hither and thither in his conquered Kingdomes, and in regard of his ſtrong holdes which he ſhall poſſeſſe he may goe, and come, paſſe and repaſſe, without anie feare of hoſtile invaſion or home rebellion, vnleſſe the word <hi>gnabar,</hi> paſſe over, doth ſignifie ſome declining or leſſening of his power, as if the Angel would affoarde ſome hope that his tyrannie ſhould not be perpetuall. But this comfort is added to verſ. 44. wherupon it ſeemeth the leſſe probable, to bee here intended, ſo as the former
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17593:21"/> ſenſe is the likelieſt. wherfore when ſuch happie ſucceſſe is ſignified in theſe wordes, and how the event hath bene anſwerable, we perceive and feele by wofull experience, rather then need to be expreſſed by anie mans ſpeech: ſince the time that the floudgates taken up, this whirling raging gulfe was ſent into the worlde, overflowing and violently bearing all away with his multitudes.</p>
                  <q>And he ſhall enter into the glorious land &amp; manie countreyes ſhalbe overthrow.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 41.</note>
                  </q>
                  <p>The largenes of his dominions is ſet out at large, and withall certaine boundes are ſet, at leaſt on ſome part, which by no meanes he ſhall overpaſſe. The firſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie made mention of is the land of the Roe or of delight and ornament, that is Iudea it ſelf, as Ezechiel ſheweth, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it the land of the Roe or of glorie, which God ſware to give to the Iſraelites after their deliverie out of Egypt, and which he gave them to poſſeſſe after fortie years wandring in the wildernes. Ezec. 20.6.15.<note place="margin">Erets hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebi. Terra capreolae.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But it may happily be doubted, what ſhould be the reaſon of this appellation, whether it be ſo called from his inhabitaunts put to flight and driven into baniſhment, as, the Roe-bucks leavinge their wounted haunts doe runne hither and thither when the houndes and hunters doe purſue them in the mountaines. So Eſay ſpeakes of Babilon deſcribing her exiled Citizens caried away, for it ſhall be ſaith he, As the chaſed Roe and as the ſheepe that no man taketh up cha. 13.14. And Iudea, whether we reſpect the firſt Canaanites, whom the land ſpued out for their horrible wickednes, or the new dwellers the Iſraelites firſt caried away by the Aſſyrians and after driven out of their country by the Romanes, and ſcattered tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the whole earth, may worthily be called a chaſed Roe. But Ezechi: in the place aforeſaid ſeemeth to bring another notation of this name: for he deſcribing Canaan from the abounding of milk and honie, as if it
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17593:22"/> had borrowed, his name of this fruitfulnes, ſaith. It is the Roe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> glorie of all landes, as if all landes did hunt and ſeek eagerly after this land as after the Roe, becauſe of the felicitie therof, as if this were the glorie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious delighte of all landes, for ſo is <hi>tſebi</hi> often vſed. I think the Spirit did vſe this word of ſet purpoſe, therby to comprehend both, their expulſion and happines, leſt her citiſens ſhould deſpaire and be quite out of heart, but in the midſt of her ſorowfull exile they ſhould think themſelves to be Gods <hi>tſebi,</hi> darlings and delight. To this ſame purpoſe is that word Armageddon, vſed in the Apocali as we have ſhewed in that place. Seing then that this is the land wherof the Angel in this place ſayth, the King of the North ſhall come into it; and he ſpeaketh of his comming as of a new thinge: for to what purpoſe ſhould be declare it as a wondrous and ſtrange thinge which was vſuall and accuſtomed? This King therfore of the Noth is not Antiochus, for whom it was no newes to come into Iudea.</p>
                  <p>He had twice before grievouſly afflicted it, verſ. 28.30. His third comming might have bene terrible but not new, if he had come, which we have prooved formerly to be farre from the truth. By the ſame reaſon is the Romane excluded whom we have ſeene before bearinge rule in the land, and making ſale therof verſ. 39. or divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it for gaine, but it moſt fitly and truly agreeth to the Turke, who at his firſt onſet was wholy taken up in ſubduinge of Europe and Aſia, on that ſide which is joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the borders of the Perſian Empire and came not in Iudea the glorious land before Zelimus, about the yeare one thouſand: five hundred and fourteen going into E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, took his journey this way and ſo by the way, won Ieruſalem by aſſaulte.</p>
                  <p>At the ſame time fell manie countries, Comogena of Syria, Antiochia, Damaſcus, alſo Tripolis, Berillus, Sidon
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17593:22"/> and alſo Paleſtina, with all the region by the ſea coaſt even vnto Egypt, which all now firſt came vnder the Turkiſh tyrannie. Yet it ſo came to paſſe by divine providence that he medled not with Edom, Moab or Ammon, for that is the cheife of the children of Ammon; as if he ſhould ſay, he was ſo farre from ſubduing theſe countries that he had no power over their uttermoſt coaſtes. We know theſe regions doe border upon Iudea, Edom to the South, Moab and Ammon toward the Eaſt, and by one common name are at this day called Arabia, the third part wherof the Turk vexed, not being content to open himſelfe a way into Egypt, through Syria, Iudea, Paleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na. From the time of that expedition, Perſia and Europe eſpecially, did hold him tacke, ſo as his warres proceeded that way no further.</p>
                  <p>Here therfore reſteth the Turk on that part of the worlde, by which fixed boundes and journey, as it were drawne and laid out, the Spirit leadeth us as it were foote by foote, to finde out this Cruel beaſt. But theſe landes were not free from Antiochus, who had the tuition of them, as it is manifeſt by Hircanus the ſonne of Ioſephus, who attempting manie things againſt the Arabians, and fearing leaſt being brought vnder the power of Antiochus he ſhould pay for his evill deedes, layd violent handes upon himſelfe, Antiochus enjoyed all his poſſeſſions. Ioſeph. Antiquit. lib. 12.5.</p>
                  <p>Afterward the Romanes with their Captaine Scaurus pierced in even to the rock of Arabia, much more did they bring vnder their ſubjection thoſe countries borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vpon Iudea, Ioſeph. Antiq lib. 14.9. And againe Auguſtus Caeſar ſent Aelius Gallus into Arabia to Attempt thoſe nations and countries. Strabo lib. 16. in Arabia, but vnder Trajanus Arabie was made a province, as Sextus Ruff. Hiſtor. Antiquit. lib. 5. de Conſulibus. It could not be therfore ſaid that theſe nations ſhould eſcape out
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17593:23"/> of the handes either of Antiochus or of the Romans, but onely of the Turk himſelfe, who as a Channel hath theſe waſts to reſtreine his raging billowes with theſe Shoares.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 42.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>verſ.</hi> 42.</note>
                     </bibl> And he ſhall ſtetch forth his hand vpon the countries and the land of Egypt ſhall not eſcape.</q>
                  <p>The Angel yet goeth forward to declare the greatnes of this tyrannie in certaine particular provinces amongſt which he ſpecially and by name expreſſeth Egypte firſt of all and ſome other regions of the Continent, as well becauſe the Iewes did there eſpecially live in exile, to whom this comfort was cheifly intended, as alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the conqueſt of theſe countries ſhould, as it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, be the laſt.</p>
                  <p>To ſtretch the hand then is to offer violence, to make warre and to vanquiſh and to bring into ſubjection againſt their wills, this rage and tempeſt was to ſpread it ſelfe into divers countries, and the Chriſtian world hath at this day wofull experience of the truth of this divine oracle.</p>
                  <p>Egypt was one among the reſt which ſhould bee van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed and ſubdued to this empire; which that ſame Zelimus, of whom we ſpake in the former verſe, brought vnder his ſubjection in the years 1515. He had indeed intended and prepared his voyage againſt the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian; But when Campſon Gaurius the Sultan of Egypt had taken Aladinus his nephew on the brothers ſide, and had ſent a proude anſwere to Zelimus, who deſired peace while he was occupyed in his Perſian warres, the Turk on the ſodaine turned all his forces againſt him. So having ſlaine himſelfe and ſcattered his armie, in the province of Comagena, he gave not over till he had pearced into Gaurius his Kingdome, of Egypt, through
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17593:23"/> Syria and Iudea, and although it did valiauntly defend it ſelfe, he did vtterly overthrowe it and tread it vnder foote. Antiochus indeed attempted warre againſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt; but he was conſtrained to depart without doing of any thinge, for all his attempts were reſtrained by one comminatorie warring of the Romans, ſo as he was fayne to relinquiſh that which he had gotten, as Ioſephus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiq. lib. 12. 6.</p>
                  <p>How ſhall we then applie theſe things to Antiochus, who was farre ſhort of the ſucceſſe of this King of the North. The Romane did enjoy this Kingdome, yet not by ſtretching his hand upon Egypt as the Turk who overcame it by force and armes, but by right of league and confederacie as all hiſtorians report. Now to find out the true events, we muſt not onely regard what was done, but after what maner and ſort alſo, wherin the prophecie is as certaine, as in fore ſhewinge the thinges themſelves, which are to be done.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 43.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Verſ.</hi> 43.</note>
                     </bibl> And he ſhall have power over the treaſures of gold and ſilver and over all the precious thinges of Egypt.</q>
                  <p>Theſe wordes doe more fully ſhewe how Egypt ſhould not eſcape, that is to ſay, it ſhould be ſubject to his will in ſuch ſort as he may freely prey upon it, make havock and ſpoile of it, which we find this Zelimus did, when he had taken Tomumbeius Mamatucus, who had made himſelf King after Gaurius his death, he tried him with a tedious and ſharpe examination about his treaſures before he would put him to death.</p>
                  <p>What hidden treaſures will not he find out and carry away, which conſtreineth the King himſelfe by torments to bewray all? how cruelly did he rage againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, who had no regard of Majeſtie &amp; honour? Of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17593:24"/> very good right did the Spirit make mention of the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den treaſure, for the ſmellinge and finding out wherof ſuch a deale of crueltie was vſed.</p>
                  <p>And when there was no more gold, leaſt anie thing ſhould be wantinge which might further his deſires, he caried away more then five hundred families out of all Egypt, ſpecially out of the Citie Memphis of the moſt wealthie and noble ranke, beſides a great multitude of women and children of the Mamatukes, whom he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to be ſlaine every one. A kinde of men indeed worthie to dye an evill death. No ſuche thinge was ever done by Antiochus. And allthough the Romans had power over the treaſures of Egypt, which they with greedines and crueltie extorted in all places by all the meanes they could, yet this power was not of the fadinge but of the flouriſhinge eſtate of the empire, whoſe time is now handled, as we have ſeene, in the beginning of the 40. verſ. Whatſoever thinges therfore are here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, as ſome waies agreeing to the Romanes, wee ſhall fynde much differing in time, ſo as the diligent and attentive reader cannot deceived.</p>
                  <p>As concerning the Lybians and Ethiopians, who ſayth hee, ſhal bee at his ſteppes: therby is ſignified that theſe nations alſo ſhal ſerve the King of the Northe, whoſe ſtepps and goings they ſhal obſerve, and ſhould ioyne themſelves as companions in his expeditions. Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia is a common name of the whole continent of the third part of the world which is now called Africa: &amp; it is a ſpeciall name of a certaine part of the countrie, which againe is diſtinguiſhed into two other Lybiaes, ſo as in the whole it is three folde. It hath not his name of Lybia the wife of Epaphus, or anie ſuch like as the Grecians would have it, but of Lehabim by contraction Lubim, as the native wordes are uſually corrupted among forraine nations, for the countrie is ſo called for the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17593:24"/> flame and ſcorching heate of the ſunne wherwith it is alwaies ſchortched and burnt. And thoſe Lehabim tooke their originall of Mitzraim Gen. 10.33. Some re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre Lubim to the root Lebab, and the forme of the nowne doth admitte this notation as the more fitt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the ſignification diſagreeing; ſeing that the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> goe before all other nations in craft and ſubtill pollicie.</p>
                  <p>But Daniel ſeemeth to uſe the word corrupted, rather by the cuſtome of nations then contracted after an uſuall and accuſtomed maner.</p>
                  <p>The Ethiopians heere or Cuſhim whoſe father was that ſonne of Cham Gen. 10.6. And although the Cuſhits did inhabite farre and wyde, in Aſia and Africa, yet they ſeem by a common and generall name, to be ſpecially pointed at which inhabite from the South of Egypt to the ſeaward. The Angel therfore ſaith that theſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhal folowe the turkiſh enſignes, or at leaſt the Turke with his ſteppes ſhall come unto them, that is to ſay, with his Emiſſaries, Baſſawes, Begoes and Agoes and other meſſengers, which he uſeth as ſteppes to overrunne farre diſtant places, and to bring them under his ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And wee know alſo that a great part of Africa, beſide Egypt: is now poſſeſſed of the Turk at this day. Arcademus Barbaroſſa the turkiſhe ambaſſadour did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive Maleaſſes the King of Tunnis of his Kingdom, whom the Emperour Charles the firſt reſtored againe in the yeare 1535. who ſix yeares after had occaſion againe to ſaile to Argiers in Africa to keep the Turk buſied in farre diſtant places to bridle and reſtreine the inſolencie of his late victorie in Europe with ſome loſſes in Africa, if it might bee. But Caeſar now arrived not with the like happie ſucceſſe as he did before, for the third day there aroſe ſuch a tempeſt and violent fall of raine, that he loſt manie of his ſhippes, gunnes and all other provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17593:25"/> yea he wanted manie thouſand of his ſoldiers, wherby he was conſtrained to depart without doing anie thinge, and to leave that whole province to the Turkes. Yet not theſe alone are in his ſteppes, but Ezechiel ſetting downe the armie of Gog, whom in the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we have manifeſtly proved to be the Turke, doth conioyne together the Ethiopians and them of Phut the furtheſt weſterne Lybians of the countrie Tingetana ch. 38.5. Now if theſe thinges be applied to Antiochus we ſhal ſee a wonderfull difference. He had no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund over Egypt alone, much leſſeover the Lybians &amp; Ethiopians whom he never came neere unto either by himſelf or by his meſſengers in anie warlike expedition.</p>
                  <p>The Romanes were of old the Lordes of all this countrie, but in their prime floriſh of their Kingdome, not at the time of the end, whither the Angel hath all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready brought us as we ſaid before.</p>
                  <q>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>veaſ.</hi> 44.</note>But tydings out of the Eaſt and out of the North ſhall trouble him.</q>
                  <p>Hitherto of the proſperous affaires of the King of the North, now folow the adverſe, and firſt by tydings. All the former paſſages have ſhewn us thinges paſt all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: for ſince Antiochus, the Romanes, Saracens and Turkes have playd their par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, who with grievous cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities have waſted and at his time doe waſt the Iewes, partly while they reteyned the religion given them from God, and partly whilſt to this day they doe wickedly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their ceremonies abrogated long agoe. But thoſe thinges which folow from hence unto the end, doe ſhew us alſo of thinges to come, as it will eaſily appeare by the particular expoſition. We have often times incountred that opinion which attributeth all theſe thinges to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus, to that intent truly that it might appeare in everie particular, how much it wandreth from the truth, wee are yet to proceed in the ſame, that we ſuffer not our
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17593:25"/> ſelves to be deceived by it, when we ſhall ſee the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and diſagreement therof on everie ſide. I doe not therfore finde what tydings from the Eaſt ſhould trouble him, except happily that rich temple of Diana in Elanois did trouble the man: yet that meſſuage was more to provoke his luſt in coveting: then to ſtrike anie feare in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. And what need was there to goe thither with ſuch a cruel minde, utterly to deſtroy all, where gold and not bloud was ſought after.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Mac.</hi> 6.2.</note> Neither was there anie forcible attempt to anie private mans goods, but onely to ſacred wealth, wherwith the Iewes often times, being more Iealouſly affected to their ſacred and holie thinges, then thoſe of Elanoies were, redeemed both their lives and libertie. And grannt him to be Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus Epiphanes, was hee ſo madde or beſide himſelfe that being affrighted with eaſterne &amp; northern tydings,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Mac.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 37.38.</note> himſelf ſhould goe into the eaſt and ſend Lyſias into the South, and ſett no guard at all toward the North?</p>
                  <p>Our learned Broughton ſawe that theſe tydings were no way likely to trouble the man, and therfore hee taketh in the Parthian warre which Florus reporteth to be betweene Pharates and Antiochus the King of Syria, in the Abridgement of Livius 59. but the learned man was decived in the name, and referreth that to Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes, which was proper to Sedetes many yeares after, Liv. li. 46. ſheweth Epiphanes to be dead, but that which he mentioneth of Antioch. l. 59. belongeth to Sedetes, as it is manifeſt out of Iuſtin alſo, who ſheweth Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus to have departed, who had to doe with Popilius the Romane legate in Egypt, at the end of the 34. booke: but the Parthian warre was of another Antiochus much younger, the brother of Demetrius that was living and taken by the Parthians, of which warre hee entreateth in his 38. book. That is therfore a vayne Parthian warre, at no hand to bee referred to thoſe tydinges.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17593:26"/> Calvin doth expound theſe thinges of Craſſus, who being overcome at Carras in a great battaile not farre from Babilon, the Romane whom he maketh this King of the North, was terrified with the report of this ſlaughter.</p>
                  <p>It could not indeed otherwiſe bee, but very grievous to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Romane to heare of the death of ſo great a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and of ſo great and well furniſhed an armie, but where are the tydings from the North? Caeſar in the mean time did ſubdue the french men, neither were there anie other northerne tumults. Where was this Cruel expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to deſtroy and vtterly to make away manie? The Romanes did not much ſtriue in the revenge of that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrowe, onely Antonie added more unto it, by the overthrow alſo of his owne forces. For whereas the Parthians brought the eagles of Auguſtus, which they had taken away at the death of Craſſus, they did it vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily and not by conſtraint as Florus ſheweth in his 4th book and 12. cha. Furthermore where did the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane plant his Tabernakle? at the glorious holie moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that is to ſaie, in Iudea the holie land, therby to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe the feare of theſe tydings; or how came hee to his end in the ſame land, who flouriſhed ſo long after and when he began to fall, he had his overthrow anie where ſave therabouts? There are manie ſuch like argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which will not ſuffer it to be referred to anie Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane. Wherfore theſe wordes belong to the Turke, whom wee have hitherto ſeeme to be meant of the King of the North, and the tydings out of the Eaſt and the North, which ſhal ſo trouble him, ſhalbe the report of the Iewes converted to the Chriſtian faith: Wee knowe this nation is diſperſed almoſt through the whole world, but yet they moſt abound in the countries Eaſt and North in reſpect of Iudea; For they be bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17593:26"/> upon their native Countrie, and the Remaines of their brethren, which were of old carryed awaie by the Aſſyrians, and inhabited theſe very places, might thither invite and allure others as often as they were to remove out of their owne countrie.</p>
                  <p>Out of both theſe regions the Iewes at length ſhal ſhew themſelves, who ſhal give attentive eare unto Chriſt. This did the Revel: 16.12. teach us before, where after the overthrowe of Rome, Euphrates ſhal bee dried up, that the Way of the Kinges of the Eaſt maie be prepared.</p>
                  <p>There have we ſhewed that this is to be underſtood of the vocation of the Iewes and that it belongeth to the very ſame time with theſe tydings out of the Eaſt, the moſt deadly and laſt warre prepared in both places doe make manifeſt. There the dragon muſtering all his forces, doth goe to a place called Armageddon to cut off and deſtroy utterly, but he doth bring deſtruction upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for that next viall doth powre out the laſt deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> upon all Gods enemies. Here the King of the North ſhal goe forth with great furie in the glorious holie mountaine to deſtroy and utterly cutt off manie, but he ſhal come to his end, &amp; none ſhal help him. Then immediately ſhal the reſurrection folowe, as wee ſee in the beginning of the next chapter. But the Apocalyps maketh onely mention of the Eaſt, becauſe the firſt greateſt &amp; chiefeſt companie ſhal come from thence, yet in the new Ieruſalem, next to the firſt gates on the Eaſt, which are ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to theſe firſt eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erne Iewes, are thoſe on the north, becauſe the brethren of thoſe parts ſhal make up the next companie of thoſe that came on flocking into the new citie c. 21.13.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Re.</hi> 21.13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> In which reſpect Ezech. doth firſt deſcribe the north gates of the holie citie reſtored; ſhewing by this mixt &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſed order (his prophecie giving the firſt to the north &amp; the Apocal. to the Eaſt) that it ſkilleth not much whether of the twaine
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17593:27"/> we ſett firſt, the deſire of both out of both countries wil be ſo cloſe ioyned &amp; almoſt unſeparable.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezech.</hi> 48.1.16.30.</note> ch. 48.<hi>1.</hi>16. &amp; 30. This conſent therfore of Daniel, doth very much confirme our expoſition of the Revelation &amp; the Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ticles, but the matter will as yet appeare more evide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, when we ſhal have gone over the reſt of Daniel. Theſe are the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings out of the Eaſt and the North, which at length ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bee noyſed farre and neere after Rome ſhalbee defaced: ſhee alive and ſurvivinge, no good newes can be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; Chriſt doth deferre that ioyfull and happie time to her fall and ruine, leaſt that loathſome harlott, ſhould be partaker of ſuch a pleaſant report. And how can it otherwiſe be, but this newes muſt be very troubleſome to the Turke, who knoweth well what a deale of miſchiefe maie therupon fall upon him? he hath enough to doe to defend himſelfe againſt us Cbriſtians of the weſt alone; what a terrour will it bee to ſee himſelfe, in the midſt of his enemies to be beſet before and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, at one time, and not onely to hazard the loſſe of his empire, but of the name of the Turkes alſo? for then ſhal that ſayeing of the Prophet be fulfilled, I have bent Iuda as a bowe for me, I have filled Ephraims hande, and have raiſed up thy ſonn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s O Sion, againſt thy ſonnes O Greece, and made thee as the ſworde of a mightie man. Zach. 9.13.</p>
                  <p>Now then will he gnaſh the teeth, fret and chafe, ſtorme and growe madde, hee will appoint choiſe offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and muſter and take up a huge armie, hee will ſet forth to warre with a full purpoſe to waſt and deſtroie all thinges, for as much as now hee will ſee the time at hand, either to quit himſelfe ſpeedily, or to periſh for ever. And the Romane Antichriſt will afoard him an opportunitie to turne himſelfe wholy to that warre, who will withhold us in theſe weſt parts with as trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome a warre as the revelation teacheth, chap. 19.19.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17593:27"/> For he ſhall reviue and remaine, a while after his forlorne and loſt Rome, as we have obſerved vpon the Apocal. 16.13. &amp;c.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 45.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Verſ.</hi> 45.</note>
                     </bibl> And he ſhall plante the tabernacle of the wrath of his judgment between the ſeas in the mountayne of holie delight.</q>
                  <p>We have heard of the tydinges and of his wicked pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſorowfull preſages of his deſtruction at hand. Now the deſtruction it ſelfe is ſet downe, a ſweet comfort to all the godlie and of all their tedious troubles, but all this wil bee finiſhed in warre: both the place and iſſue hereof are ſet downe in this verſe As concerning the place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he deſcribes it by his proper markes; he ſheweth in a word what maner of proviſion he ſhould make in this place, he ſayeth, He ſhall plant the tabernacles of the wrath of his judgement, for ſo I render and tranſlate <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Ahole Aphadno: the Greeks doe retaine, the Hebrue word entire <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and he ſhall plant his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle Aphadno; but Symmachus re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth it <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſtable, And he ſhall ſpread the tabernacles of his ſtable, that is to ſay a ſtable wherin his horſe ſhall ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. The vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar latine verſion doth imitate the Gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kes, And he ſhall plant his tabernacle Aphadno. The reſt which I have ſeene doe thus with one conſent, and he ſhall plant the taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of his pallace.</p>
                  <p>The ſtrangenes of the word which is no where elſe vſed in the Scriptures, and the conveniencie of the matter made me thorowly to obſerve the notation therof, which ſeemeth to be compounded of three wordes, Aph and Din, and the affixe of the third perſon ד the wrath of his judgment? as if he would ſay, Hee ſhall plant the taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of wrath, wherby he ſhal procure vpon himſelfe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; everlaſting deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; a moſt ſignifica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t word vſed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17593:28"/> of purpoſe, as it ſeemeth, moſt divinely to comprehend in a breif ſumme admirable conſolation. He ſhall indeed attempt deſtruction vnto others, but the miſcheif ſhall fall upon his owne head: he ſhall finde and feele that in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf which he intended for others.</p>
                  <p>Reverend Broughton ſaith, it is a Babilonian word of frequent vſe in the Babilonian Talmud: but it may be the Iewes did often inſert the word, found in Daniel in their writings in that ſignification which themſelves moſt fancied, though it were not in common vſe with the vulgar Babilonians. The fit compoſition of theſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew wordes doth make this opinion more then proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Now for the place of the warre, he ſaieth, Between the ſeas: but where abouts is that? or rather where is it not? ſeing the whole land is an Iland? he therfore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreines this largenes in the next wordes: In the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of holie delight, in the mountaine Tſebi, of the Roe or del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght, that is to ſay in the land of Iudea, as we have ſeen before in verſ. 41. Hence let us take knowledge which ſeas theſe be the river Euphrates and the Syriach arme of the Mediterranean ſea, as in the 72. Pſalme verſ. 8.</p>
                  <p>And he ſhall have dominion from ſea to ſea, from the river vnto the ends of the earth: for firſt the Iewes ſhalbe here gathered together who now live as exiles and out of their owne countrie. All the Prophets ſpeak of this returne which they ſhall advaunce and take in hand, not for religions ſake, as if God could not elſwhere be worſhipped, or as if it were of neceſſitie to bring in the legall worſhip againe, but not to ſtriue anye longer as ſtrangers and inmates with forraine nations and that the admirable goodnes of God might openly appeare vnto all men, now againe pitying his people whom he had eſtranged from himſelfe with ſo longe a divorce: Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto alſo will the Turke come in haſt to oppreſſe this
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17593:28"/> newly returned people. He wil compaſſe the campe of the ſaints ſaith Apocal. 20.9. and the beloved Citie, But Ezechiel<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eze.</hi> 38.8.</note> moſt playnly ſaying. After manie daies thou ſhalt be viſited in the later years, thou ſhalt come into the land which is brought back from the ſword and is gathered out of manie people, againſt the mountaynes of Iſrael, which have been alwais waſt, when he ſhalbe brought forth out of the nations, they ſhall all dwell ſafely; and there is much more cha. 38.8,</p>
                  <p>The tydings therfore out of the Eaſt ſhall call the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie into the holie land: not to Chinais whither Antio. went, nor to Babilon whither the Romans went, to be revenged upon the Parthians, ſo as if there were no other mark of the King of the north beſides the very place of the warre, his perſon could not be concealed from an attentive reader.</p>
                  <p>The iſſue of the warre wil bee moſt lamentable, for he ſhall come to his end and none ſhall helpe him: becauſe it ſhalbee brought to paſſe not ſo much by mans power and forces as by Gods owne mightie arme, gloriouſly ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing it ſelfe from heaven, as it is Apoca. 20.9. But fire ſhall come downe from God out of heaven to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure them. And I wil plead againſt him, ſaith Ezech. 38.22. with peſtilence and with bloud, and it wil raine vpon them and vpon his bandes, and vpon the manie peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that are with him an overflowinge raine and great haileſtones, fire and brimſtone. What help and aide can come againſt theſe darts and arrowes? O Turk, thou ſhalt therfore periſh, not only the Prince himſelfe, but alſo the principalitie it ſelfe; thy name ſhalbee vtterly raced out and thou ſhalt be tormented everlaſtingly, both for thy horrible impietie againſt God and alſo for thy barbarous wickednes and crueltie againſt men.</p>
                  <p>Thou art left as another Pharao ſoone to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne with violent ſtormes of the fierie lake, that both
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17593:29"/> the great name of our God may bee made more famous, as alſo to afoord to all the Saincts the argument of a new ſonge of thankſgivinge. Such is therfore the King of the North, who when he ſhall periſh in the holie land, he can neither be Antiochus nor the Romane, who came to their ends in other places.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The text of the whole 12. CHAP.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>1</hi>
                        </bibl> And at that time ſhall Michael ſtand vp: the great Prince which ſtandeth for the children of thy people, and there ſhall be a time of trouble, ſuch as never was ſince there was a nation, even to that ſame time: and at that time thy people ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, every one that ſhall bee found written in the booke.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>2</hi>
                        </bibl> And many of them that ſleepe in the dust of the earth, ſhall awake ſome to everlaſting life, and ſome to ſhame <hi>and</hi> everlasting contempt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>3</hi>
                        </bibl> And they that bee wiſe, ſhall ſhine as the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the firmament, and they that turne many to rightouſneſſe, as the ſtarres for ever and ever.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>4</hi>
                        </bibl> But thou, O Daniel, ſhut vp the words, and ſeale the booke, even to the time of the end: many ſhall runne to and fro, and knowledge ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>5</hi>
                        </bibl> Then I Daniel looked, and behold, there ſtood other two, the one on this ſide of the banke of the river, and the other on that ſide of the banke of the river.</p>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:17593:29"/>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>6.</hi>
                        </bibl> And <hi>one</hi> ſaid to the man clothed in linnen, which <hi>was</hi> upon the waters of the river: How long <hi>ſhall</hi> it bee to the end of theſe wonders?</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>7.</hi>
                        </bibl> And I heard the man cloathed in linnen which <hi>was</hi> upon the waters of the river, when he held up his right hand, and his left hand unto heaven, and ſware by him that liveth for ever, that it ſhal bee for a time, times, and an halfe: and when he ſhall have accompliſhed to ſcatter the power of the holy people, all theſe things ſhal be finiſhed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>8.</hi>
                        </bibl> And I heard, but I vnderſtood not: then ſaid I, O my Lord, what <hi>ſhall</hi> bee the end of theſe things?</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>9.</hi>
                        </bibl> And hee ſaid, Go thy ways Daniel; for the words are cloſed vp and ſealed, till the time of the end.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>10.</hi>
                        </bibl> Many ſhalbe purified and made white and tryed: but the wicked ſhal doe wickedly: and none of the wicked ſhall vnderstand: but the wiſe ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>11.</hi>
                        </bibl> And from the time that the daily <hi>ſacrifice</hi> ſhall be taken away, &amp; the abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that maketh do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, ſet vp, <hi>there ſhall bee</hi> a thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred &amp; ninety dayes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>12.</hi>
                        </bibl> Bleſſed is hee that waiteth and commeth to the thouſand three hundreth and five and thirty dayes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>13.</hi>
                        </bibl> But goe thou thy way till the end be: for thou ſhalt reſt, and ſtand in the lot at at the end of the dayes.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <div type="analysis">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:17593:30"/>
                  <head>THE ANALYSIS <hi>or Reſolution.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HItherto of oppreſſours, now their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce is handled, which in the generall and in this kinde, is both out of great affliction v. 1. and afterwards to an vnchangeable condition and eſtate verſ. 2.3. but in his qualitie, it is both ſealed, verſ. 4. and hath a double oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time, the firſt proper to the Angel, whoſe preparation ſheweth the number of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and the place, verſ. 5. But the conference doth conſiſt of a queſtion ver. 6. and an anſwere, conſiſting partly in geſture, and partly in wordes, verſ. 7. The ſecond oppoſition of the time is ſuch, as a man at length ſhould vnderſtand alſo, the occaſion wherof was alſo the ignoraunce and the queſtion of Daniel verſ. 8. The anſwere of the Angel is partly negative and refuſinge, v. 9. partly conſolatorie, as wel univerſally, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to all Saints, (whom he ſheweth this dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and obſcuritie ſhall nothing hurt ver. 10.) and withall yeeldeth help an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> aſſiſtaunce to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the double time expreſſly determined firſt verſ. 11. the ſecond verſ. 12. as alſo particularly, which belongeth to and concerneth Daniel himſelfe, verſ. 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="exposition">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:17593:30"/>
                  <head>THE SCHOLIA or Expoſition.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Verſ. 1.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1.</note>
                        </bibl> And at that tyme ſhall Michael ſtand vp, the great Prince.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THis laſt Cataſtrophe and turning, doth proſecute three things in order: who ſhall deliver, from whence, and whom.</p>
                  <p>Some would have Michael here the defender, to be Chriſt and it is very certaine that he is the great Prince; yea by farre the greateſt of all, the Prince of his elect peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who hath delivered his church alwaies and will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver it herafter, yet the name of Michael here ſeemeth to be ſome certaine Angel whoſe miniſterie the great Prince will vſe in this battaile. In the later end of the tenth chap. before, he is ſpoken of as a certaine helper, with whoſe aide that glorious Angel aſſiſted, ſeemeth notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to complaine of his being alone, There is none that holdeth with me, ſaieth he, in theſe thinges but Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael your Prince.</p>
                  <p>But more plainly there in verſ. 13. And lo Michael one of the cheife or firſt princes. for Chriſt is not one of the cheife princes, as if he were of a certaine or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Angels, and had a Companion of power, but all the Angels, as ſervitours doe Miniſter vnto him. But thou wilt ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Acad Haſharim, is not one of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but firſt of the princes, verily <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is of order ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, when it is joyned with nownes of time, as in one of the moneths, that is to ſay, in the firſt day of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. Levit. 23.24. And ſo with this our Prophet, in one yeare of Darius, that is in the firſt, Dan. 9.1. From
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17593:31"/> whence in one of the Sabaoths for the firſt daye of the weeke. But the ſame word joyned with others is, for the moſt part of number not of order, as behold the man is become like one of us: Gen. 3.22. He doth not mean as the firſt of us: of which ſort are manie other places. That may be added alſo, that the Archangel Michael in Iude 9. Doth put off the Divil to the Lords judgment as if himſelfe had not power and authoritie to reſtraine him, which yet notwithſtandinge Chriſt doth exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe. Mar. 1.25. as in manie places elſwhere in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
                  <p>Neither is it likely that the Apoſtle, if he had meant Chriſt, would not have called him by his proper name, eſpecially when he doth bring his argument from the greater, whoſe force is much leſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed, if that which is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of all, be not called by his owne, but by a farre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour title. Yet doe I not ſo diſpute of this, as if I meant willingly to contend with anie man about that matter, but onely to finde out truth, wherof very great care is to be taken as much as may be, even in the ſmalleſt matters. Neither is it of neceſſitie that things muſt be done by the miniſterie of an Angel from heaven, in ſuch ſort as no part therof ſhould be acted by man, but Chriſt may raiſe and ſtirre up ſome excellent man in whoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he may preſent a viſible Michael, as in that battaile of Michael and the Divil in Apocal. 12. we have ſeene: But what kinde of miniſterie ſoever it ſhalbee; in what maner this Prince ſhall come prepared and furniſhed to the battaille, it is at large declared in Apocal. 19.11. Secondly whence he ſhall deliver, is from ſuch a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome time, as was not the like from the begining of the nation vnto that very time. The Turk is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies intolerable even in peace, reſt, and vacation, how outragious wil hee bee, when he ſhalbee afraid of his owne overthrowe? He hath ſtriven elſwhere about
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17593:31"/> ſome Countries, or at the uttermoſt about the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, but now he muſt fight for his life, where he muſt either overcome, or elſe not onely undergoe the yoak of ſubjection, but be utterly deſtroyed and die with extreme torments. He hath often times in vaine caried, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt infinite forces into the field: how will hee be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed now, when he ſhal perceive all now ſhalbee hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at once for ever?</p>
                  <p>Out of theſe ſtreights of time, anie one maie eaſily conjecture what horrible turmoiles, the Cruel beaſt ſhal make, but alſo on the newe and Chriſtian peoples part there wilbee no leſſe grievous a tryall, when they ſhal ſee this horrible and fearfull tempeſt, immediately to follow the faith which they ſo lately had profeſſed? For they may imagine God to be angrie becauſe they have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken their fathers religion and have embraced chriſtian, which their anceſters did ſo hate, therfore the Spirit doth foretell the grievous troubles of thoſe times, leaſt anie man by the ſharpenes therof ſhould fall from the truth. God doth vſually turne tbe rage and furie of the adverſaries unto his owne praiſe and glorie, if other eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capes be ſtopped up, he ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eth a paſſadge thorow the ſea, bringeth out of the lions den, and preſerveth ſafe in the fierie furnace, neither doth hee ſtill the raging waves vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till wee ſee our ſelves allmoſt loſt: Wherfore as of old in Egpt, ſo ſalvation will now ſodainly ſhine forth, but then eſpecially when all thinges ſeeme deſperate, and paſt recoverie.</p>
                  <p>But how is this affliction moſt grievous? of all former onely which ſome one greater ſhould after ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed? not ſo, but of all without exception, for it ſhal out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrippe all the former and it ſelfe ſhall be laſt, which an everlaſting deliverie ſhall preſently folow, for hereunto is joyned the reſurrection, after which no calamitie is to be expected of the Saincts. How therfore ſhould
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17593:32"/> it either agree to either Antiochus or Romane, who, whatſoever miſcheife they did, it was but a flea-biting to this miſerie of a thouſand ſix hundred yeeres, wherin as yet the Iewes doe lye buried.</p>
                  <p>But this fit or ſharpe aſſault is not come as yet, ſeing the deliveraunce is not yet happened, which ſhal fall out in the midſts therof. Who ſhal bee delivered, they are firſt noted by their nature, then by grace: by nature, Thy people, By grace, Every one that ſhalbe found written in the book. That ſheweth the nation of the Iewes, which were Daniels people, comming of Iacob the ſame common root and ſtock. So in the beginning of the verſe alſo ſtanding for the children of thy people: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he teacheth that this deliverance is not preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly but to be expected in their poſteritie, namely their Children, but how manie ages after, ſhal appeare afterwards.</p>
                  <p>This prophecye therfore is proper to the Iewes, but thence it will not folowe alſo as proper to the time of Antiochus, ſeing the Iewes maie be afflicted as Gods people, howſoever they ſuffer not for Moſaical cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, as it will fall out when they come to the faith. I would that worthie Broughton had conſidered this, he would not have ſo drawne all with a wrye necke unto Antiochus.</p>
                  <p>But there ſhal bee alſo a choice and difference in this people: Theire deliveraunce ſhal not be ſo confuſed to bring all to eternall life, but thoſe onely which together with this outward ſafetie from theſe great dangers, ſhal bee by ſaving faith adopted for ſonnes, whoſe name<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God in his everlaſting decree hath written in the book of life, for, it is not in him that willeth or runneth, but in God that ſheweth mercie: neither is it in our power to receive faith or beleeve, but is onely theirs who have the earneſt pennie of election. It is very likely therfore that ſome
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17593:32"/> of the Iewes wil hold ſo obſtinately their legall rites and inſtitutions, that neither with the famous deliverance of their nation, nor with that exceding glorie wherwith the truth ſhal then flouriſh, will they ſuffer themſelves to be ſeparated from their ſuperſtition.</p>
                  <q>And manie of them that ſleep in the duſt of the earth ſhal awake.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>verſ.</hi> 2.</note>
                  </q>
                  <p>Such hath bene the trublous eſtate whence they ſhal be delivered; The condition into the which they ſhall ſhift and paſſe, is waking out of the duſt of the earth, which is afterward layd downe by a diſtribution of ſaincts and reprobates in this verſe; and againe of ſaincts alone in the next verſe. As concerning the wakinge, all our expoſitours that I could ſee, doe refer it to the laſt reſurrection of the bodies. Some Iewes contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe doe apply it to the reſtoringe of the Church, which they ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie ſhal bee in this world. Wee muſt freely and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently ſearch on which ſide the truth is, all prejudice laid aſide. It maketh againſt ours, that all theſe thinges, namely the end of the former chapter &amp; firſt verſe of this, are ſo linked together in a continuall courſe and order among themſelves, for that is meant by the band of time in the beginning of the chapter, At that time ſhall Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael the Prince ſtand vp, as if he ſhould ſay. At what time the kinge of the North ſhall pitche his tents in the land of tſebi Iudea it ſelfe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall that great trouble op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them, then ſhall happen this admirable delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, then ſhall this reſurrection be accompliſhed: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore howſoever in other places paſſage may be made from the birth of Chriſt to his ſecond appearinge, yet in this place it cannot, where ſuch a band doth come-in betweene.</p>
                  <p>And vnleſſe we doe allow of this connexion, what a huge heap would there bee in the prophecie, what a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17593:33"/> gulfe to let ſcape and ſkip a thouſand ſix himdred years and more, I know not how manie, eſpecially which hath gone ſo leiſurely and orderly to this very place and was cheifly ordeined for the Iewes, to whom he affoar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no comfort at all, if he paſſe and flie preſently from Chriſt firſt exhibited vnto the latter end of all thinges. This one thinge may ſeeme ſufficient to refute the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition not onely of this verſe, but alſo of all which ours doe bring vpon the ten laſt verſes of the former chapter, which they wil not have reach beyond the firſt comming of Chriſt, when as yet the Angel hath gone ſtep by ſtep through all ages from thence as wee have made it plaine I hope.</p>
                  <p>Seing therfore all theſe thinges are neceſſarily cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled and joyned together among themſelves, if that voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the King of the North into the land of <hi>tſhebi,</hi> be either the expedition of Antiochus or the Romanes into that countrie, then this reſurrection which immediatly foloweth, is either not proper, or if it be proper, then that expoſition of Antiochus and the Romane is not true and naturall. But you will ſay, Let us hazard the loſſe of that expoſition rather then ſuffer this of the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to be taken ſo from us. Let it be a continuall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly prophecie, let it be ſhutt up at lenght with the laſt reſurrection; but the Angell wil not have it ſo, who ſpeaketh ſo exactly as if he did it of purpoſe to meet with this ſtrange expoſition.</p>
                  <p>Manie of them, ſaith he, that ſleep in the duſt ſhall awake; the reſurrection (ſo properly called) is common to all, as manie as from the firſt Adam doe ſleep in the duſt, but when this is onely of ſome, it is manifeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o be ſome other then that which is properly ſo called. But ſome will ſaye, Some are put for all. Once happily or twice in Rom. 5.15.9. But we muſt not ſtart from the naturall ſignification but where there is neceſſitie of the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:17593:33"/> figurative here nothing inforceth to leave the proper: but contrariwiſe there is a neceſſitie to reteine it: for ſeing this reſurrection is the ſame with the deliverance in the former verſe, made indeed out of the book of life, after the manner of the reſurrection, and being of one onely people of the Iewes, as was obſerved before, they are ſaid well, Manie to be awakened, when the men of one nation and not of all mankind do ariſe: therfore our Broughton doth not well tranſlate it, for the manie of them that ſleep in the earth of the duſt ſhall awaken, for the manie is as much as the multitude or the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall of them that ſleepe; all together from the minde and purpoſe of the prophecie.</p>
                  <p>So dangerous a thing it is to put-in anie thing of our owne in doubfull places, which are rather to be left pure and intire, then to be prejudiced by anie additions. It ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſomwhat alſo, that the reward of the beſt here, is much inferiour to that which all ſhal have there at the laſt, in the reſurrection all the righteous ſhal ſhine as the ſunne in the Kingdome of their father Matth. 13.43. but in this they whoſe reward is greateſt, ſhal not exceed the brightnes of the ſtarres.</p>
                  <p>But they, ſaith hee, that turne manie to righteoſnes ſhall be as the ſtarrs for ever and ever. Its a manifeſt diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene that and the heavenly Crowne. Beſides, which juſtifie, ſaith hee, intimating a place for doctrine in this reſurrection, wherby godlie mindes being indued with the knowledge of Chriſt doe enioy true righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes and holines, when as in that laſt reſurrection, prophecie ſhal ceaſe, and all this pollicie wherwith the Church is now governed upon earth, 1. Cor. 13.8. and laſt of all the Angel both knoweth and teacheth others the daie of this reſurrection, as wee wil ſhew in the laſt verſes of this chapter: for the end of theſe wonders wherof they inquire afterward, verſe 6. and 8. doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:17593:34"/> this reſurrection, the laſt terme of the former pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie and a thinge worthy of admiration: but the day of the laſt reſurrection is hid from the angels themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, yea from Chriſt himſelfe as the ſonne of man, much more from Daniel or anie other of the Prophets Marc. 13.32. Theſe thinges therfore make againſt the proper expounding of the wordes. Calvin objecteth one thing againſt the figurative, which is the reſtoring of the church neiter will that ſtand, ſaith he; which is ſaid, ſome ſhall riſe to life, others to ſhame &amp; contempt, if this did onely agree to the church of God, ſurely none ſhould riſe to ſhame and contempte. But it may be anſwered. That the church is a field mingled at leaſt with tares among the good corne, a net not altegether without bad fiſh, a houſe not without ſome veſſels to diſhonour: wherfore it is needfull to preferre ſome particular reſtoring of the church, before that generall expoſition of the generall reſurrection. Neither is the certeintie of the bodies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any whit at all weakened therby. This doctrine is confirmed by other ſcriptures above all exceptions: and this very place whoſe proper ſenſe and meaning we have cleered doth make ſomwhat alſo for confirming therof. The Spirit of God would not ſo often and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently uſe this allegoricall reſembla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, if it did not therby declare the thing ſhould moſt aſſuredly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to paſſe in his time. Otherwiſe it were an eaſie matter to avoid, all the promiſes confirmed by this type, as no whit more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine then the reſurrection wherof there is litle or no hope at all,</p>
                  <p>But the holie Prophets doe leave no ſtartings back, whilſt they bring the matter grounded upon manifeſt promiſes, and reſted upon by aſſured faith to confirme the ſame. Faith therfore looſeth nothing, although it doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly acknowledge what is due to every place. What is this reſurrection then? the full reſtoring of the Iewiſh
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:17593:34"/> nation &amp; their vocation to the faith in Chriſt, for ſo is our Converſion to God often called, in the Scriptures; the time ſhal come, ſaith Chriſt, and now is, when the dead ſhal heare the voice of the Sonne of God, &amp; they that heare it ſhal live. Io. <hi>5.25.</hi> Awake thou that ſleepeſt, ſaith the Ap. Eph. 5.14. &amp; ariſe from the dead &amp; Chriſt ſhal give thee light. But the Iewes ſpecially ſhal riſe by belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving &amp; riſing out of their troubles, of whoſe reſtoring the world hath litle hope. The mightie hand of God wil raiſe up theſe dead carkaſſes, elſe it were incredible that this duſt ſhould live againe: wherfore the Apoſt. ſpeaketh of the Iewes, what ſhal the receiving bee but life from the dead Ro. 11.15. as purpoſely bringing light unto this &amp; ſuch like places. This reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then is the ſame wherof rhe Apo. ſpeakes c. 20.12.13, for this followeth the utter overthrow of Gog &amp; Magog, that is preſently added to the deſtruction of the Turkes, as we have expounded: &amp; both Gog &amp; the Turke doe make theſame enemie, as wee have ſhewed in the Revelation at large. This is that reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection wherof Eze: c. 37. with this onely difference, that Ezech: deſcribeth the firſt converſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Iewes by life reſtored to dead bones &amp; Daniel expreſſeth their firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion by the tydings out of the Eaſt, and therfore the battle of Gog and Magog doth folowe the reſurrection with him. But in this and alſo in the Apocalipſe, it doth goe before it. This is that revocation of the Shulamite wherof in Canticl. 6.12.13. Returne O Shulamite, returne, that wee may look upon thee: Or rather that wiſh that foloweth (for the renovation doth rather belonge unto the tydings of the Eaſt in our Daniel) O that one would give thee as a brother unto me ſucking the breaſts of my mother, finding thee without I would kiſſe thee, yet I ſhould not be deſpiſed. So as an admirable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Scripture doth ſhine forth every where to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme a matter altogether vnknowne to the world, &amp; we have expected nothing leſſe then that almoſt theſe manie
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:17593:35"/> generations. Such is the reſurrection then, the diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of them that riſe doth followe, of ſome to eternall life and of others to ſhame and everlaſting contempte. For as converſion to Chriſt is ſpecially called reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, yet notwithſtandig the generall deliveraunce from enemies, which was common to the whole nation, doth in ſome ſort reſemble it, when they ſhal lift up their heads and ſtand upon their feet, who lately were troden under foot of all, and were almoſt brought to duſt with the weight of their long and tedious afflictions.</p>
                  <p>Out of whom, thoſe whoſe hearts the Spirit ſhal endue with love and faith, ſhal ſurely awake and come out of the graves having now obteined the dignitie of the children of God: Who ſhal enioy eternall life, not onely becauſe they ſhal have the fruition therof in heaven, but alſo becauſe there ſhal bee a perpetuall felicitie in earth, not to be ſteined with former troubles of the former ages anie more, but it ſhal continue pure and ſpotleſſe until their departure into heaven, for now wil God wype all teares from their eies, and there ſhalbee no more death, nor ſorow nor crying nor paine, for the former thinges are paſſed away Apocal. 21.4.</p>
                  <p>But the reſt who being partakers of the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce ſhal yet perſiſt in the wicked blindnes of their hearts, they ſhal riſe in deed, but to eternall deſtruction; ſeing after this time there is now promiſe of mercie to them, and of calling them to the faith, wherby alone wee apprehend and laie hold of ſalvation: for all the Iewes will not give conſent to the ſame truth, but ſome of them will preſevere and perſiſt in their ould hardnes of heart, howſoever God ſhal give a cleere teſtimonie to his ſonne by ſubduing all their adverſaries. There is no place therfore left in the new Ieruſalem for the fearfull and unbeleevers and the abominable and murtherers and whoremongers and ſorcerers and idolaters &amp; all lyers,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:17593:35"/> which is ſpecially ſpoken of the obdurate and hardened Iewes, allthough the men of the ſame ranke in all other nations alſo ſhall bee in the like eſtate and condition Rev. 21.8.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 3.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </note>
                     </bibl> And they that are wiſe ſhal ſhine as the brightnes of the firmament.</q>
                  <p>The other diſtribution of them that riſe, is of ſaincts onely, wherof ſome be people ſome bee the teachers: both are illuſtrated by a ſimilitude, they of the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, theſe of the ſtarres. For I doe agree with learned Calvin, who taketh Hamaſhchilim intranſitively, as alſo a litle after in the tenth verſe, where with out doubt knowledge is not tied unto teachers, which thence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, becauſe Hamaſhchilim, the wiſe, are there oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Leriſhagnim to the wicked, for onely the ſaincts, &amp; all of them are truely wiſe, but the wicked, allthough they excell in pollicie, craft and ſubtiltie, in all trades &amp; cuſtomes of living, yet notwithſtanding are emptie and void of all ſound and true wiſedome, and are in very deed ſaid to bee fooles, as Salomon doth often call them.</p>
                  <p>But now all the people and whole companie of the faithfull ſhal bee pure &amp; cleane, ſhininge with bewtie of intire holines, like vnto the firmament it ſelfe, whither no cloude aſpireth, nor anie earthlie pollution aſcendeth to caſt anie aſperſion or blott therupon. The firmament is often covered all over with thicke cloudes, and taken out of our ſight, but heere it is ſpoken of, not as it often ſeemeth to us, but as it is in its owne nature.</p>
                  <p>But they that juſtifie others by teachinge, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing, exhortinge, reproovinge and comfortinge, which are parts and duties of the Teachers, and they which enioy publicke office in the Church ſhal bee the ſolideſt and cleareſt parte of their ſpheare and compaſſe, and ſhal
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:17593:36"/> become ſhining ſtarres wherwith this firmament ſhal be bewtified and adormed, themſelves in the mean time enioying the chieffeſt glorie. So in the firſt chriſtian Church the miniſters were ſtarres, which one like the ſonne of man walking betweene the candleſticks, d d beare in his right hand, Apo. 1.20.</p>
                  <p>Theſe teachers of the Iewes ſhal enioy like glorie, which are precious ſtones in the Apoc. 21.19. wherof is built the wall of the new Ieruſalem.</p>
                  <p>It is to be obſerved here that the Doctors and Teachers are deſcribed by that preſent dutie not formerly paſt: for matſedikim doth ſignifie them that doe juſtifie, and not that have juſtified or turned to righteouſnes; by which argument we have ſhewed before, that the laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection is not heere intended in this place, where there wilbee no uſe of preſent teachers, but the former paſt labours onely ſhall be rewarded. Farthermore we maie obſerve, that here is a leſſe reward both of people and teachers then that which God hath laid up for all his owne againſt the laſt daie, who ſhal bee like as the ſunne.</p>
                  <p>If therfore the Angel doe heere now ſpeak of the greateſt glorie of the ſaincts, why ſhould he ſignifie it by the reſemblance of the firmamente? beſides what ſingular thing have the teachers, if they atteine to no more then that which is common to the teachers here in this life? Theſe are all ſtarres as the place even now ſpoken of did teach us: but now they are alſo called angels whoſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ſimilitude ſeemeth to be the higheſt top of our felicitie and happines. Indeed they are called angels but by reaſon of their miniſterie onely, and not of their preſent glorie. The Spirit therfore would ſhew us by the rewards themſelves, that this is ſome other reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction then that which ſhalbe of all men at the laſt.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:17593:36"/>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 4.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 4.</note>
                     </bibl> And thou Daniel ſhut up the wordes and ſeal the book.</q>
                  <p>Hitherto is the firſt part of the chapter, now he com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth to the reſt, where firſt is a ſealing conſiſting of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, &amp; the putting in of a tacite &amp; cloſe objection.</p>
                  <p>The precept is of ſhutting the wordes and ſealing the book even to the time of the end. But how ſhould this bee? Should Daniel keep it to himſelfe alone? wherfore then did he commit it to writing? The Angel woulde have him write it in theſame wordes, and after the ſame maner which he had received it, to adde nothing of his owne by way of expoſition to cleere the matter. Daniel knew well how obſcure and darke theſe things would be to the readers, and he himſelfe vnderſtood the whole matter very well, as he witneſſed in the beginning of the viſion, and he vnderſtood the thing, &amp; had underſtanding of the viſion ch. 10.1. therfore the learned and eloquent man could have cleered the obſcurities with ſuch wordes if he might freely have done it, as none of the ſimpleſt ſort need to have bene anie where gravelled therat. But the Angel doth not give this libertie but commaundeth to wrap it up in the ſame obſcuritie wherwith he ſawe it covered at the firſt deliverie therof from himſelf. This doe I take to be the true &amp; proper meaning of this ſhutt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; ſealing: for Daniel had heard theſe thinges of the Angel, neither had hee anie other way to ſhutt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> up but by writing obſcurely and not in open &amp; playne termes. But wherfore doth he bid ſhut up the wordes and ſeal the booke? Are the book and theſe wordes the ſame &amp; all one? It often cometh to paſſe that ſome ſhort and litle writinge is called a booke, as the booke of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Ieſus Chriſt Mat. 1.1. &amp; ſuch like. But happily heere in this place the wordes are this very prophecye, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of the tenth chapter, &amp; the book all his
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:17593:37"/> viſions in generall which he is commaunded to hide in a profound ſtile, hard to be knowne and to put them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a book; after God had laſt ſpoken to him in this kynde of viſions, but the former viſions were alreadie written before, ſo as it is better to referre, words and booke, to the ſame thinge; yet ſo, as the thinges ſhould be kept cloſe and not be hid for ever, but onely to the time of the end: of what end? Of a perfect end, or ſoone after to be perfected: nigh at hand, as it ſeemeth and a litle before the end, when thinges lately buried in obſcure darknes ſhal be brought forth into open light. Daniel might have objected, that ſo the elect ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the fruite of a moſt holie and divine revelation. The angel meets with it, as if he ſhould ſaie, Let not that trouble thee, for manie ſhal come to and fro, and knowledge ſhalbe increaſed, that is to ſaie, although theſe thinges be hard and difficult, yet ſome wil take great paines in ſearching out the truth, and by wiſe diſcourſe gather one thing of another, wil level very neere, yea and hit the mark it ſelfe, and will much increaſe knowledge; which thing indeed wee have ſeene come to paſſe both in the Iewes and in our owne men, who by diligent ſearch have found out manie remnants of this gold ſcattering heere and there, and therby have brought much profit both to themſelves and to the Church.</p>
                  <p>But for what cauſe would God have theſe thinges ſhutt up for a time?</p>
                  <p>Firſt that the wicked by ſeing ſhould not ſee, and by hearing ſhould not heare, wherfore Chriſt ſpake in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables to the vnbeleeving Iewes, and Iohn was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to ſeale up thoſe things which the thunders uttered. Apoc. 10.4.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, That ſecuritie ſhould not growe upon the Saincts by the expectation of a long time, to whom the opinion of an end alwaies approaching ſhould bee profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:17593:37"/> whereby they may have their Lampes alwayes in a readines.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, that there might be a teſtimony of Gods truth in thoſe auncient times, when the wicked at length ſhall know that thoſe things were foretold many ages before, which themſelves doe finde moſt true after it is too late.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Laſtly, becauſe this obſcuritie ſhall not take away all underſtanding of the Saincts, but ſhall whet only their diligence in ſearching, to whom the Angell promiſeth a further profiting and proceeding, ſeing by their godly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and diligence, God doth make over to the godly all his myſteries &amp; ſecrets in Chriſt.</p>
                  <q>And J Daniel looked &amp; behold two standing.<note place="margin">
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ. 5.</note>
                  </q>
                  <p>So is the ſeating, now followeth the firſt deſigning of the time; the preparation whereof doth propound unto as two other Angels, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> place where they ſtood. The number ſeemeth to be added for the confirmation of the whole matter. In mens Courts God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed every matter ſhould be eſtabliſhed by the mouth of two or three witneſſes, Deut. 19, 15. After the ſame manner the more are ſent, that the matter might be more confirmed, and humane infirmity regarded &amp; provided for. Now might the Prophet try his right by Law with the Angell if he had deceived, or the thing foretold him ſhould not com to paſſe. The place where they ſtood was at the bank of the river, one at one ſide of the bank, and the other on the other ſide, and the river was Hiddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kel, as we learne by the 10. chap. verſe 4. the third river of Paradiſe, Gen. 2.14.</p>
                  <p>It is not certainly knowne whether the Prophet were bodily preſent by this river, or the ſight thereof were afoarded him after a prophetical manner. If it be this,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:17593:38"/> there is ſome great matter in it, why this alone ſhould be offered to his very viewe above all the reſt, but if he were bodily preſent, which I rather thinke, Daniels company flying away for feare, chap. 10.7. neither can it be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, that he maketh mention rather of the river then of the region and country: And we ſhall ſee aſſuredly that of the fowre viſions, which were ſhewed to Daniel, three of them were at the waters. And not without good cauſe, when as viſions doe foreſhew the affaires of nations and people to be done in ages to come, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters do both lively reſemble the troubleſome tempeſts of worldly buſineſſes, with the variable and inconſtant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of people, and alſo thereunto are frequently uſed in ſcripture, as in Ezech. 26.19. When I ſhall make thee a deſolate cittie, by bringing up the deepe upon thee, and great waters ſhall cover thee. But waters doe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diverſity of the things thereby ſignified. In the firſt viſion the fowre Windes of heaven ſtrove upon the great ſea, and fowre great beaſts came up from the ſea, chap. 7.2.3. becauſe as the Sea is the collection &amp; gathering together of waters, ſo there was intreated of the matters of all people, which ſhould all be diſturbed with theſe fowre Kingdoms. The ſecond viſion was at Vlai, no ſea, but only a river unknowne, not famous, not ſett out with any note at all of any excellencie, ſo in that viſion the Empire of the whole world was not intreated off, but ſome particular nations, the Medes, Perſians, and Grecians, in which the prophecy ſtoppeth his narration, as it were in ſome creek of a great ſea, and a river, drawne and derived out of the deep, chap. 8.2. The laſt viſion was at Hiddikel, a particular River alſo, but ſuch a one as flowed out of Paradiſe, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the matters therin hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, doe ſpecially reſpect a particular people, but holy &amp; elect, whoſe ſpring &amp; originall doth come out of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, the infinite grace of a mercifull God, which runneth
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:17593:38"/> thence along thorow the ſtock of the holie Patriarchs in all ages, as it were thorough a channell.</p>
                  <p>The former viſions were alſo ſhewed for the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſake onely, but they declared flouriſhing nations. Firſt, the fowre great Monarches, afterward the Medes, Perſians, &amp; Grecians: This alone ſheweth the full delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the holy people, and therefore they were given at the ſea and unknowne waters, like to people of no account with God: but this was given at the holie River, that he might more lively ſet before our eyes the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that auncient &amp; holy people, by the election of grace. Such a River therfore is it. Now, the Angels doe not ſtand both on one ſide, but are ſeverally placed, and keep both the bankes, becauſe God defends this people on every ſide by his Angels, to whom he hath given in charge, not onely to be carefull of ſome of their matters, and careles of the reſt, but to perfect all things which doe concerne the ſafetie of his elect. This is a great comfort in time of ſo long a divorce, when they underſtand that their God careth for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that there remaineth a ſeed of election amongſt them, though the blind world ſeeth it not, as being farre hidden from mens eyes.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ver. 6.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ver. 6.</note>
                     </bibl> And he ſaid vnto the man clothed in linnen.</q>
                  <p>The conference of the Angels followeth, and firſt a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion before, which we have both the perſons propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it and to whom. The propounder of it was one of the Angels, which ſtood at the bankes. Both doe not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire by words, although the deſire of knowledge of it was common to them both. It was ſufficient for the one to receive the anſwer, neither was it materiall which of them demaunded it; Therefore whilſt one ſpeaketh, the other expecteth in ſilence, modeſtly obſerving order, the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:17593:39"/> authour whereof the holy ſpirits have alwayes before their eyes.</p>
                  <p>The Angell whom he enquireth of, was clothed in Linnen, to wit, garments, for Badim are Prieſtly garments, made of fine Linnen, peculiar onely to the Prieſt, whence happily they have their name for <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Bad,</hi> is a ſole and ſingular thing that doth agree but to one, &amp; therefore the Prieſts are noted by theſe garments, as Doeg is ſaid to have ſlaine fowreſcore and five perſons wearing a Linnen Ephod, 1. Sam. 22.18. David went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Ark in ſuch an Ephod, 1. Chro. 15, 27. but it was extraordinary, and he that was a perpetuall type of Chriſt our King might for a time joyne or uſe a Prieſtly habit, moved therto no doubt by divine inſpiration. But as theſe garmens did belong onely to the Prieſts, ſo were they proper onely to the holy place, for when he was to goe from the altar, although in his ſacred function they were to be putt of, and others putt on, Lev. 6.11. yet the Levites ſeeme to have uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d them in carying the Arke from the houſe of Obed Edom to the cittie of David, 1. Chron. 15.27. yet it may be theſe garments were not the Baddim of the Prieſts, nor that Ephod of David, but ſome ſpeciall ornament, for joye and ſolemnity of the time, which David wore in common with the Levites, whoſe dutie it was to carry the Ark, as if he had longed and leaped for joy to be counted in the number of the ſacred and holy miniſters.</p>
                  <p>The other word <hi>Buts,</hi> there uſed doth ſeeme to ſignifie this difference, ſo as <hi>Bad</hi> in the end of the verſe may by a common name ſhew the like garment both of the Kings and of the Levites, neither the one nor the other uſing that which belonged onely to the Prieſts and the holie place.</p>
                  <p>For to adde one thing more becauſe we have entred
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:17593:39"/> vpon this matter of garments; theſe were ſo proper and peculiar to the holie place that they were to be vſed if the prieſts were there converſant, though upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion then for religion; wherunto tendeth that of Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus, That whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Herod reedified the temple &amp; could not himſelfe for religions ſake enter into the inward parts, he procured the framing therof by the prieſts, a thouſand of them at his coſt were clothed with prieſtlie robes, and were not vnſkilfull, ſome in maſonrie, ſome in carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie lib. Antiq. 15. 14.</p>
                  <p>Theſe garments doe therfore ſeem to proove him to be Chriſt, who is the onelie prieſt worthie to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted with in all doubtfull matters, whoſe lippes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve knowledge, and at whoſe mouth the law is to be inquired. He is alwais in the temple, in the midſt of his owne, &amp; therfore is alwais clothed with holie garments: which yet will more appeare, if we conſider him ſtanding upon the waters of the river.</p>
                  <p>The other two angels ech of them kept his banke, looking to their taſks enioyned, but the care of all lay upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this, and therfore as the Spirit moved vpon the firſt waters, ſuſteining them in that confuſion by his mightie power Gen. 1.2. ſo Chriſt watcheth over the affaires of his Church, which would quickly come to vtter ruine if they were not ſupported by his power.</p>
                  <p>But it is to be obſerved, if this be Chriſt, Michael is not, for hee doth playnly diſtinguiſh between himſelfe &amp; Michael in the end of the tenth chapter, and there is none that holdeth with me, faith hee, in theſe thinges but Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael your prince.</p>
                  <p>Such are therfore the perſons conferring: the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion it ſelfe, How longe ſhal it bee to the end of theſe wonders? that is to ſaie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal the e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of theſe wonders be? The Angels doe deſire to behould and prie into the ſecret myſterie of redemption, unto which earneſt ſtudie
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:17593:40"/> they might privately give themſelves, and enquire theſe thinges apart, if their example were nothing pertinent to kindle and enflame our induſtrie.</p>
                  <p>Who therfore can without great blame be negligent in inquiring after theſe thinger, wherof he ſeeth the angels ſo greedie, though excelling in multiplicitie of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thinges. Neither is this their ignoraunce feigned: for to what end ſhould the anſwerer ſo earneſtly ſweare in a matter of no doubt, for theire ſakes eſpecially did he ſpeak ſo earneſtly by aſſeveration, knowing that Daniel could not vnderſtand his anſwere. And wee know that the Angls, though they be of an excellent vnderſtandinge of all things created, yet are ignorant of manie thinges till they be further informed. For they are not onely ignorant of the laſt daie, but alſo of that manifould wiſdome of God in the myſterie of the Goſpell, which it now made knowne by the Church unto principalities and powers in heavenlie places Epheſ. 3.10. They deſire to have theſe things ſhewed unto them, wherby they might the more magnifie the great and highe creatour for his infinite wiſedome.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 7.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 7.</note>
                     </bibl> And J heard the man clothed in linnen.</q>
                  <p>The anſwere is confirmed by an oath, the forme wherof is expreſt by geſture and wordes. The geſture is the lifting up of both handes to heaven; That is to ſay, towards heaven. It was an ancient cuſtome in ſwearinge to lift up the right hand to heaven, as if they would call him to bee preſent for a wittnes, whoſe glorie and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie doth ſhine eſpecially in the heavens: but he here clothed in linnen, by lifting vp both his handes doth ſeriouſly ſhew ſome excellent matter, and doth more
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:17593:40"/> pearce and affecte the mind with a ſenſe of the higheſt Majeſtie.</p>
                  <p>As often as the name of God is to be vſed, the minde is to be raiſed vp to as great a reverence as may poſſibly bee, and how much more of us miſerable men very duſt and earth, when as the mightie and holie Angels doe ſo prepare and diſpoſe themſelves at the very mention of him. Oh you moſt filthie beaſts which doe in mockerie pollute his holie name in your comon talke. The ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne wordes are by him that liveth for ever. In all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, when the minde is not capable of the divine exceeding greatnes, an attention is ſpecially to be faſtened on that part, as I maie ſay, which is moſt powerfull to kindle and ſtirre up our preſent faith. Wheras now therfore the times are ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of, he moſt fitly bringeth in God living for ever, who can beſt of all beare witnes of the appointed periods of all thinges, whoſe alone is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>But now let us come to the matter it ſelfe; which ſets downe the time two waies, both by a certain diſtributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and by a full diſperſion of the holie people. The diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution is more generall and indefinite, which may as well agree to anie age, for what age is there wherin we maie not finde a time, times and a halfe? But the other member, and when he ſhal have accompliſhed to ſcatter the power of the holie people, All theſe thinges ſhal be accompliſhed; doth revoke that generalitie vnto cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine boundes, neither doth it permit a wandring into all ages, but makes it proper to one certaine: as if he ſhould ſay, All theſe things ſhal have an end, not at every time, times and half a time, but at one certaine time, when hee ſhal make an end of ſcattering the holie people: which plaine and perſpicuous ſentence makes me think that thoſe thinges can no waies agree to Antiochus.</p>
                  <p>For although we graunt the time of his afflicting the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:17593:41"/> Church to fall fitly into this diſtribution, wherof not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding we ſhal ſee by and by: Had this people alſo an end of their calamities with Antiochus? Did that bleſſed reſurrection and happie, happen to the Iewes at his death? What ſcattering from the firſt beginning of the nation, is comparable to this, wherof they have had now ſuch miſerable experience theſe manie ages ſince their crucifiing of Chriſt? It was not more grievous to be afflicted in their owne countrie, then to be ſcattered through the whole worlde: to want their countrie, goods, eſtates &amp; liberties, and to hold their lives at other mens pleaſures wherſover they live: beſides the diſtribution fitteth not.</p>
                  <p>The moſt learned Tremellius doth ſo render it. After an appointed time, appointed times, and part of time. The wordes are thus properly: At, or for an appointed time, appointed times and a halfe. For I thinke <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>heſi</hi> is no where uſed but for an halfe or equall part of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. But before where the ſame matter is handled, it is Vphelag guiddan, and the diviſion of time. c. 7.25. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it, but becauſe the word phelag was doubtfull, this prophecie being more plaine, as the latter alwaies uſeth to be, doth by name expreſſe: what part hee meant and ſpeaketh of before, ſure halfe. Can we then after this faſhion devide the time wherin Antiochus afflicted the Iewes? Our writers doe referre theſe thinges unto that time wherin the dailie ſacrifice was taken away by Antiochus, and the abominable ſacrifices of the wicked gentiles were ſubſtitute and put in liew therof. But his time is farre from the accounte: For this abomination laſted but three yeares and ten daies at the moſt: The .15. daie of the moneth Chiſleu in the 145. yeare this impietio began 1. Mac. 1.57. and in the yeare 148. the 25 daie of the ſame moneth, the abomination was put awaie and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emple clenſed, 1. Mac. 4.52. therfore if one yeare be
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:17593:41"/> a time, 2 yeares, times, ten daies are diſtant from the halfe 172. daies.</p>
                  <p>But Ioſephus doth expreſly confirme the aſſiduitie and continuance of the daily worſhipp to have ben inhibited for three yeares and ſix moneths, In bello Iudaico lib. 1.11. But the Macabean contrarie, That day the heathen had defiled it, in the ſame daie was it made new againe, 1 Ma. 4.54. where are then the ſix moneths of Ioſephus, if it were reſtored, the ſame day that it was defiled? Therunto agreeth the ſecond booke of Macab. 10.5. That day the temple was polluted by ſtrangers, on the very ſame daie it was clenſed againe. Yea Ioſephus himſelfe a more faithfull wittnes elſewhere contradicted himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>And they offred whole burne offrings, ſaith he, upon the new altar and that fell out upon the ſame daie wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their holie things had beene prophaned three yeares before Antiq. lib. 12. 11. See how exquiſitely he ſpeaketh, ſhewing it alſo to bee the ſame day of the yeare not of the weeke.</p>
                  <p>Therfore the true time of this abomination was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely three yeares onely, we made mention lately of ten dais more, but by them was ſignified the beginning of that wicked enterpriſe revealed; What then came into Ioſephus minde to make an addition of ſix moneths more? Surely, as it ſeemeth, from the miſunderſtanding of this ptophecie, which hee thought to be referred to Antiochus, he would have fitted the time againſt all truth of hiſtorie.</p>
                  <p>But you wil ſay, though theſe thinges doe not fitly agree to that three yeares, yet they agree well enough to the terme of two thouſand three hundred daies, which time of raging was appointed before to Antiochus by the Angel cha. 8.14. for if we allow for a time 657 daies, for times 1314. for halfe a time 328. the ſumme wil be
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:17593:42"/> made up wanting but one day. Truly this conjecture co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eth neerer to the truth then the former, and ſheweth what a neere conjunction there is betweene theſe two enemies, who have the like time of the raging allowed unto, yet it wandreth much from the meaning of this prophecie: for this diſtribution is the very ſame with that of c. 7.25. and belongeth unto it. But that litle horne of the 7. c. which is the ſame with this time, is not the ſame with the litle horne of the 8 chap. which is certainly Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus Epiphanes, and therfore wee ſhall not doe well to conſound the times &amp; to give that to one which is proper to another. Not to ſpeak of the viſion of the 7. c. which was at the ſea, but that of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ight at the river of Vlai, &amp; thoſe in the ſeventh were writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the comon tongue of the heatheniſh Kingdome, that the comon prophecie might come abroad unto all.</p>
                  <p>Theſe in the 8. in the proper and mother tongue of the holie people; by both which the prophet would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate that firſt prophecie to be more generall, This more particular, and thoſe which folow thence to the end of the book.</p>
                  <p>To let theſe thinges paſſe, I ſaie: It is moſt certaine, that the litle horne of the eight ch. is of the thirde great Monarchie, wherof c. 7.17. for it is of the goate, which is called a leopard, chap. 7.6. with his 4 winges and 4 Heads, therfore hee maketh one Kingdome with the goate and leopard. For the hornes muſt not be pulled off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heads, and ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her maner of Kingdome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of thoſe and of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe, wherfore all theſe doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto the third Empire and Monarchie, which is of the Macedonians. But the litle horne of the 7. chap. is of the fourth great Monarchie, except we will labour to make them but three onely, which the Angel ſaith are foure c. 7.17. contrarie to the ancient hiſtories, which doe acknowledge no ſuch diverſitie in the hornes from the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:17593:42"/> beaſt it ſelfe, whoſe the hornes are, nor obſerve anie ſuch thing in Antiochus: wherfore a new Kingdome ſhould begin from him. He reckoneth the yeares of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from Alexander, 1. Mac. 1.11. &amp; ſo conſtantly tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe that whole narration. Surely if a new government was to begin from thence, the Spirit had directed his pen to bring the accounte, from his firſt beginninge after the maner of other Kingdoms. Furthermore the litle horne of the eigth chapt. doth come out of one of the foure hornes of the goate, but the litle horne of the 7. cha. came up amonge the other ten hornes.</p>
                  <p>Beſides this horne reigneth till the hornes bee caſt downe, and the ancient of dais did ſit ch. 7.9. that is to ſaie, till all the Kingdomes of the world be overthrowne, and all principalitie come to Chriſt, as it will ſoone com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to paſſe after this blaſphemous horne be cutt off.</p>
                  <p>But preſently after Antiochus had not the Kingdome, at leaſt that moſt ample one of full glorie, whom all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhould ſerve, as it is there in verſe 14. It were te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to gather all thoſe thinges which ſhew a difference. Theſe few maie be ſufficient to the underſtanding and lovers of the truth.</p>
                  <p>Seing therfore theſe thinges cannot agree unto Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochus, we muſt ſeek out ſome other Kingdome, which we ſhal finde to be no other then the Turkiſh, whither the prophecie hath brought us allreadye, as we have ſhewed. This is that litle horne amonge the ten, coming out of the fourth great Kingdome, to witt the Romane, moſt famous in the Apocalypſe with the ten hornes. chap. 12.3. &amp;c. with whoſe iron teeth and nailes of braſſe, all the reſt were devoured and broken in peeces. The time of this litle horne was limited before cha. 7.25. and is heere repeated againe as the but &amp; bound of that matter which the Angels dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. For the man clothed in linnen anſwereth. Then ſhal bee the end of theſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:17593:43"/> wonders, when the blaſpemous Kingdome of the Turkes ſhal come to an end, then God ſhould make an end of ſcattering the holie people and of powring out his wrath anie further upon them.</p>
                  <p>But what ſhould be the time of this tyrannie, is more plainely underſtood by the revelation, where is given him an howre and daie and a moneth and a yeare ch. 9.15. which ſumme commeth to 395 yeares, every daye being taken for a yeare, as we have there ſhewed. By which entire number graunted we may now vnderſtand the reaſon of the diviſion, for a time is one hundred yeares, times 200. yeares, halfe a time 50. which whole ſpace if we number from the beginning of the Turkiſh power anno 1300. it wil end at lenght at the yeare 1650. but 45. remaine ſtill. You will ſaie, The reaſon is becauſe the Apocal. ſetteth downe the laſt time of the Turkiſh name, but the Angel heere doth ſet downe the beginning of his ruine and alteration, which deſtruction we ſhal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſee to be ſet downe in his expreſſe numbers at v. 11. &amp; 12. folowing: as we have formerly heard.</p>
                  <p>Firſt the tydings out of the Eaſt ſhal trouble him, then ſome yeares after his utter ruine ſhal folow in the land of <hi>Tſebi</hi> 11. <hi>44. 45.</hi> But the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtribution uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d in this place reacheth to the tydings and no farther.</p>
                  <p>Therfore ſo is the end of the wonders, when all theſe thinges ſhal be fullfilled, that is to ſaie when the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſhal bee, the glorie of the ſaincts ſhal ſhine, the glorie of the teachers ſhal bee chieffeſt, and all other thinges brought to perfection wherby Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhal have the preheminence over all; Which thinges if anie man judge to bee meant of the internall kingdome allready obteined, he deſtroieth the prophecie, which is ſpecially converſant in foretelling thinges which ſhal be accompliſhed, being proper to certaine places and times, and not alike comon to all alike:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:17593:43"/> whereof what obſervation or pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>diction or admiration can there be, as is of theſe thinges which in the former verſe are called wonders?</p>
                  <p>It is to be obſerved, that the ſame diſtribution here in this place uſed in Apoc. 12.14. are not of the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, for that of the Apoca: is of 42 moneths, this of Daniel is onely of 13. and certaine dayes.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 8.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 8.</note>
                     </bibl> And I heard, but underſtood not.</q>
                  <p>Hitherto the conference of the Angels and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction belonging unto them. Now he commeth to Daniel. The occaſion is his ignorance and a queſtion the holy man heard, but he underſtood not. A young beginner is not capable of that which the Schollers of the upperforme doe eaſily &amp; quickly conceive.</p>
                  <p>A notable proofe of difference betwixt the heavenly &amp; earthly Schoole. An obſcure declarat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on ſufficeth them, which our dulnes no more perceiveth then the blind man doth the ſunne beames, although it be of the moſt acute and wittieſt: for who is more acute then Daniel? But how is Daniel now ignorant of that which he underſtood before? Had he forgotten it? It was the ſame diviſion of the ſame Kingdom in cha. 7. and a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine angell being aſked of the whole matter, made knowne unto him the interpretation of the wordes, ch. 7.16. There the continuance of the tyrannie onely was ſignified by that diſtribution, which was ſufficient to underſtand that viſion.</p>
                  <p>But now another thing is demaunded when the end ſhould bee. Now continuance of a certaine part of any thing, unleſſe we know where the count is to begin, doth leave the minde in doubt floting or wavering with a confuſed notion onely.</p>
                  <p>This is therfore that which he deſired to know, with
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:17593:44"/> the expectation whereof he might comfort the tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his preſent greife. But happily he is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all blame in that he ſo curiouſly enquireth into the times.</p>
                  <p>Indeed Chriſt gave his Diſciples a check for aſking ſuch things: It is not for you, ſaith he, to know the times and ſeaſons which the Father hath putt in his owne power, Acts 1.7. and how was it that Daniel thought not thus? Surely, if it concerned me to know theſe things, the angell would have ſpoken plainely, and have fitted his ſpeech to my capacity, but it ſeemeth he would have me reſt in the certaine expectation of things to com to paſſe one day, whereupon he did uſe ſuch a ſolemne oath, &amp; would have me to ſearch no further when they ſhall be accompliſhed.</p>
                  <p>Surely, the angell by not graunting his requeſt doth ſeeme ſecretly to reprove it: yet not ſo, but ſome ſhould at length underſtand thoſe things, elſe he would not have added ſuch expreſſe bounds of the matter: and that ſaying of Chriſt, is not ſimply and abſolutely to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, but in part, and in ſome ſenſe. For Paul doth define certaine times, &amp; all things are moſt accurately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to Iohn in the revelation. Therefore he would not have his Apoſtles too carefull of the times, which did ſo little concerne their callings, but above all things to be diligent in preaching of the Goſpell, wherein conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth the very life of ſalvation.</p>
                  <q>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9.</note> And he ſaid: Go thy waye Daniel for thy words are cloſed up.</q>
                  <p>The Angell anſwereth, &amp; firſt by refuſing to impart that which he demaunded. <hi>Go thy way,</hi> ſaith he, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with thoſe many ſecrets, which have been already revealed unto thee: there is a certaine meaſure of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:17593:44"/> for every one, beyond which we may not paſſe. Every man ought to conteine himſelf within his bounds, whatſoever notable and remarkable thing is to fall out u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>till the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſiah be manifeſted in the fleſh. Thou haſt undoubted knowledge abundantly, cleerly and exactly: that which from that time ſhall after come to paſſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thou ſee the continual courſe thereof unto the later end marked out, yet the very moments of time thou muſt not know, for theſe words are cloſed and ſealed up till the time of the end. Thou muſt not onely ſeale unto others the things delivered before in obſcure termes, as thou conceiveſt of mee, but alſo the reaſon of the times, for things to be done after the comming of Chriſt is ſhutt up from thy ſelfe: the underſtanding of them is not to be found out, before the appointed time is come, and the end draw neere, wherein all things ſhall be perfected and fulfilled.</p>
                  <p>This is the ſumme of the Angels anſwer, and we ſee how men in vaine in all ages have troubled themſelves in the calculation and account of theſe things. Theſe dark queſtions have framed the Laberinth with intricate win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</p>
                  <p>How unapt are we of our ſelves, to foreſee things to com, when we faile ſo fowly here &amp; there, though the light of moſt certaine truth be held out unto us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we are not therefore to ſtick in mens great names: This know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and ſearch is not from humane capacity, but from divine revelation, if not extraordinary, yet the minde muſt be enlightened from above, and ſpecially at that time when as the conſummation and end ſhall be at hand &amp; before the doores.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:17593:45"/>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 10.</note>Many ſhall be purified, and made white and tryed..</q>
                  <p>A generall conſalation. Daniel might have feared leaſt, that the ſaincts being deſtitute of ſo cleere a light, might daſh upon ſo many grievous offences, &amp; at length fall into many gulfes of deſtruction. The Angell meets with it, and biddeth him not to be anxious and penſive in that reſpect. They ſhould ſuſteine no loſſe at all by the obſcuritie of thoſe things: for both the holineſſe of profeſſion ſhall be manifeſt and certaine, and the wiſe ſhall gett underſtanding.</p>
                  <p>Both theſe members are expreſſely laid downe, and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrated alſo by a putting to of the contraryes. The ungodlineſſe of the wicked, which ſhall doe wickedly, is oppoſed to the conſtancie of profeſſion, and ignorance of the ungodly, to the underſtanding of the wiſe. As for conſtancie, it is more profitable to the godly to live alwayes in expectation of their Lords comming appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, then to underſtand the delay thereof for a long ſeaſon, conſidering the great infirmityes of us all, yea the wiſe virgines alſo ſleepe whilſt the Bridegrome tarryeth, And when the ſervant beginns to thinke with himſelf, that his Lord will delay his comming, he will fall a ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his fellow ſervants and maidens, and will eate and drinke and be drunken. Therfore this obſcurity doth bring this commodity with it, to drive away ſecurity, and to make the minde allwayes vigilant and attentive, for it yeeldeth a certaine preſent hope; which will not ſuffer them to be filthy or vile, but doth ſpurre them on to go couragiouſly forward without intermiſſion.</p>
                  <p>Hence it commeth to paſſe, that no dangers doe terrify the Saincts, but they gett and gaine ſingular profitt by them, according to the manner &amp; greatnes of every triall;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:17593:45"/> for they are diſtinguiſhed into a threefold degree, for they are either certaine light ones or more greivous, or very great.</p>
                  <p>The firſt ſort ſhall make the Saincts pure and cleane, as we doe purifie things, which have not gotten much filth, either by a ſleight wyping or rubbing or ſpunging of them: Or if a garment have drunk in deeper any filth or ſpott, that it cannot be cleanſed without greater pains, the triall ſhall be nothing elſe but a certaine whiting, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a more troubleſome and ſharp triall, according to the quality of the filth more deeply ſoakt in, which yet notwithſtanding ſhall not exceed the boundes of puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying.</p>
                  <p>But if it be needfull to break veſſels, which are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, and very filthy, and to caſt them into the fire, they ſhall be caſt into the furnace, for no other end but to be melted, and to be made afreſh new and holy veſſels. Surely, a very great comfort to the godly, whether they be purified or wyped lightly over with lighter afflictions, or be whited with ſome ſharper tryals, as under the fullers feet, or laſt of all with the greateſt they be melted in the furnace of the hotteſt fire.</p>
                  <p>But it muſt be obſerved, although certaine words be here repeated, which were uſed formerly, cha. 11.35. yet it will not therefore follow to be the ſame perſecution. Theſe are common effects of every affliction, there are alſo the Paſtors by name expreſſed, but this no leſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the common people.</p>
                  <q>But the wicked ſhall doe wickedly.</q>
                  <p>This is the oppoſite member of the firſt part, as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity ſhall drive away ſecurity from the good, ſo it ſhall increaſe it in the wicked: For when they ſhall ſee no fear before their eyes, they will think there is no danger at all:
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:17593:46"/> therfore they wil looſe the reines to their luſts, give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to pleaſure, and take their eaſe, after a mocking faſhion demaunding, where is the promiſe of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming? For ſince the Fathers fell aſleepe, all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue as they were from the beginning of the creation, 2. Peter 3.4. But let no man be moved with their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, ſeing the Spirit hath foretold the ſame ſo long before.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond member is of underſtanding, whereof all the wicked ſhall be voide, for they obſerve no events, and thoſe which they ſee with their eyes, they attribute to nothing leſſe then to divine providence; the God of this world doth ſo blinde their eyes, and deprive them of all light of underſtanding, that they ſee not their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction before they have plunged themſelves therinto, without all hope of eſcape.</p>
                  <p>But the elect doe otherwiſe, which amidſt the great darknes of worldly things doe alwayes ſee ſome twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, by guidance whereof they may walke in ſafety: for they doe alwayes drawe from the divine oracles, that which may ſerve for their comfort and inſtruction, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever to the world they be inextricable, or ſuch as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be diſſolved.</p>
                  <p>This therefore doth the Angell affirme, that ſome ſparkes doe alwayes ſhine in the wiſe in the midſt of this darknes, as much as may ſuffice for their ſeverall times &amp; ages: to ſuch wiſe men, I ſay, which doe wholy depend upon the will of God, which doe not ſuffer the works of God, to paſſe away by them without profitt, which call to remembrance the things paſt compare and lay to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether things preſent, uſe great diligence in ſearching of the Scriptures. To theſe wiſe which have, ſhall more be given, knowledge ſhall be increaſed, faith ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed; neither ſhall obſcurity hinder them any thing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obteyning that which is needfull or profitable. It is to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:17593:46"/> be obſerved that the word <hi>Maſhchilim,</hi> when it is oppoſed to the wicked, is not taken for the teachers alone, but for any of the common ſort of beleevers.</p>
                  <q>And from the time that the dayly ſacrifice ſhall be taken away.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 11.</note>
                  </q>
                  <p>Hitherto was comfort from the freedome of danger, now there is help of underſtanding afoarded, though not unto Daniel himſelf, who had anſwer before to be gone, and that the thing was cloſed up, and ſealed, yet ſo as not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he ſhould declare and leave it to poſterity; whereby before the end of dayes, they being better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the event of things, might have ſure wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the admirable truth and wiſdom of God.</p>
                  <p>Let us dive into this deepe and bottomleſſe pitt, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by divine aſſiſtance, if happily he will graunt us to bring forth to light that which had hitherto layne hid in the bottom of deepe darkneſſe.</p>
                  <p>There is the more hope of a happy endevour and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt herein, by reaſon of the end now approaching, whereunto the underſtanding of theſe thinges is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed.</p>
                  <p>Verily, I doe unwillingly encounter with other mens learned judgments, and I would refraine the very naming of them, but that, as I am perſuaded, neceſſity doth other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe enforce.</p>
                  <p>But I hope that good and reaſonable men and lovers of the truth will not take it amiſſe to have thoſe things removed out of the way, which doe hinder the right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of things, when as themſelves alſo have taken all prayſworthy labours, to finde out the truth, and have freely taken away all whatſoever they knew did hinder the ſame.</p>
                  <p>There is a twofold time here laid downe, certaine and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:17593:47"/> limited, but neither of them doe at all belong to Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus: For in that, the firſt whereof in this verſe of 1290. dayes is referred to that time, wherein Antiochus Eupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, the Sonne of Epiphanes did by his Letters pattents or chatter permitt and confirme to the Iewes the worſhip reſtored by Iudas Macabeus from the time of the deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation made by his Fathet Antiochus; The calculation or account doth not agree: For the true time of the deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, as we have ſhewed b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fore in ver. 7. was juſt thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> whole years to a nayl, or ten dayes more at the uttermoſt.</p>
                  <p>To the decree, made by Antiochus the Sonne, the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenth day of the moneth Xan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icus, 2. Maca. 11.33. (which moneth anſwereth to Niſan of the Hebrews, as Ioſephus in his <hi>Antiqui: lib</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.) there are added other 108. dayes more: for ſo many fall out betw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ene the 25. of Chiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en, and the fiftenth of Xanticus. The ſumme of all theſe is onely a 121<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. dayes, which want of the number ſett downe by the Angell 77. dayes.</p>
                  <p>But if any will beleeve Ioſephus his fable, wherof we have ſpoken in the ſeventh verſe, who doth adde of his owne ſix moneths, to the time of the deſolation: which whole ſpace of three yeares and ſix mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ths doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foard 1272. dayes, yet notwithſtanding eighte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne dayes are wanting to this ſumme. But if we joyne 108. dayes to theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee yeares &amp; and ſix moneth, the ſpace to the decree of Antiochus the Sonne, then there will be 90. dayes over and too manie: ſo will this ſpace and time no way agree with it ſelf; not to repeat other matters, whereby we have before evinced ſufficiently, that the Angell hath nothing to doe with Antiochus from the 36 verſe of the former chapter.</p>
                  <p>Calvin of happy memory did well ſee, that this could not be underſtood of the prophaning of the Temple, which was done by Antiochus, therefore doth apply it unto the Romans, but will have the number of the dayes
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:17593:47"/> to be taken allegorically, as if the Angell had ſaid to this effect, although the time of affliction may ſeeme very long, even to 1290. dayes, yet we muſt not diſpaire, nor be out of heart of ſuch a great number, but alwayes to call to minde, although affliction remaine a time and times, yet there will follow afterward but halfe a time. But for that the Angell would have uſed ſome uſuall &amp; ordinarie number, it falleth out often times, that 7. or 10: or a hundred, or a thouſand, or ſome ſuch round and common number is putt for an indefinite: but no man will uſe unaccuſtomed particulars in common ſpeech, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he intended ſome juſt and certaine ſumme.</p>
                  <p>Beſides that, what myſtery hath ſuch ſentence in it? What needeth that to be ſealed or ſhutt from Daniel, or any other, which is the common doctrine of all times? It is well knowne to all the Saincts, that the very longeſt afflictions ſhall come to an end at length: neither could Daniel be ignorant thereof, if the former diſtribution had meant any ſuch thing: wherefore we muſt not reſt in any common doctrine, but we muſt finde out ſome thing proper and peculiar to times and places, without which it is no prophecy.</p>
                  <p>There are many other interpretations, but not of any moment and authority, as to hinder the truth at all, and therefore I will let them paſſe.</p>
                  <p>Now then to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcover and declare the matter, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of grace given unto us, in theſe words the Angell teacheth two things; Firſt, the very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree and ſett time, from whence we are to beginn to number and account; afterwards the continuance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. That is ſett out by a double note or marke; One is of taking away of dayly ſacrifice, the other is of ſetting up of the abominable deſolation.</p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:17593:48"/>
                  <p>There is mention made in Daniel divers times of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king awaie of the dallie ſacrifice ch. 8.11. and 9.17. and 11.31. Now it is out of all controverſie, that all theſe places doe belong vnto two times onely, and to two men by whom it ſhoulde be taken away; Antiochus and Chriſt: whether of theſe doth the Angel ſpeake of? we have ſhewed before both by the number of the daies, &amp; by other arguments alſo, that it cannot be referred to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt therfore is to be vnderſtood, who by his death hath aboliſhed the ceremoniall lawe of ſacrificing: which is alſo made plaine by the maner of ſpeaking, where An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus is ſpoken of, there is allwais added ſome ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of wickednes, of putting downe the truth, of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing and contempt of holines or of ſome ſuch like, for becauſe hee by violatinge the daily ſacrifice did abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and take away the lawe: but when Chriſt is ſpoken of, it is only ſaid abſolutely, He ſhall make the ſacrifice to ceaſe or take it away as in this place, becauſe he did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh it, not by violatinge and breaking it, but by fullfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it. Muſt we then begin to number from his death? not ſo, but the other part of the ſett time is to be added, And to ſet vp the abominable deſolation.</p>
                  <p>It is hard and hidden indeed what time theſe wordes doe meane: yet we muſt labour to fiſh and finde it out by comparing it with other places.</p>
                  <p>It would be tedious to repeat all other mens judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. I will content my ſelfe with the bringing forth mine owne, which I leave and commend to the godlie &amp; learned, as alſo all thinges elſe of mine to be weighed &amp; examined. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Shiekats doth ſignifie Abomination &amp; execration or curſing, but it is attributed to divers things according to the differing reſpect and ſtate of the time: which Homonymie, that is, when divers thinges
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:17593:48"/> are ſignified by one and the ſame word, hath peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deceived ſome.</p>
                  <p>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fore Chriſt yt was a very abominable and accurſed thinge to take awaie the legall ceremonies which God himſelfe did inſtitute and deliver to the fathers to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly obſerved, whence Antiochus is ſaid to ſet vp the deſolating abomination ch. 11.31. After Chriſt, who brought an end to the legal worſhip by fullfilling the truth of all ſhadowes in himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>It was no leſſe odious and hatefull to obtrude and thruſt upon God an old worſhip antiquated and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed. Wherunto Eſaie ſeemeth to have reference, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the name of the Lord, He that killeth a bullock is as if he had ſlaine a man, he that ſacrificeth a ſheepe as if he cut off a dogs neck, he that offereth an oblation as if he offred ſwines bloud, he that burneth incenſe, as if hee bleſt an idol, yea they have choſen their own waies and their ſoule delighteth in their abominations cha. 66.3.4. God in deed doth worthily deteſt heatheniſh ſuperſtition, but for men brought vp in underſtanding of divine thinges to hate and perſecute the truth, and to diſſemble and faigne holines and pietie with an adulterate and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeite worſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ip, as the Iewiſh natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth ſince they rejec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſt, is a moſt lothſome abominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before God. May not that alſo be the meaninge of that before in ch. 9.27. Where after the ſacrifice abrogated by Chriſt, there foloweth deſolation upon the winge of abominations? Let us ſee breifly, if you pleaſe, as alſo to bring ſome light and evidence happily to a place very difficult and intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate: The wordes are thus; And he ſhal confirme the covenant with manie for one week, &amp; in the midſt of the week he ſhal cauſe the ſacrifice and oblation to ceaſe, &amp; upon the wing of abominations that maketh deſolate, and until the conſummation and that determined, he ſhal poure upon the deſolat. chap. 9.27.</p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:17593:49"/>
                  <p>Having ſhewed in the beginning of the former verſe the Iewes horrible wickednes, in putting the Meſſiah to death; he declareth afterward, what puniſhments, thoſe that are guiltie of ſo great wickedn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, ſhould vndergoe.</p>
                  <p>Theſe ſaith he are two, The firſt is the deſtruction of the citie and ſanctuarie, which he deſcribeth in the reſt of the verſe, and hee do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h free them from a doubt in the beginning of the next verſe. For it might be demanded what ſhould become of Gods worſhippe, the ſacred and holie places being demoliſhed and caſt downe. The Angel doth prevent it and ſheweth both that Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe whilſt he lived, ſhould make a new covenant, and confirme it unto manie, and alſo by his death ſhould at length put an end vnto all legall ceremonies, that there ſhould he no need after that, either of the citie Ieruſalem or of the temple to worſhip God.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond puniſhment is of the People which he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſheth by a double condition: Firſt of the Nation in ſome ſort as yet ſtanding, and entire, then ſecondly broken altogether and troden vnder foote. The two wordes <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Meſhomim and ſhomem, deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating and deſolated, or making and made deſolate, doe ſignifie this difference to vs: for that is active of ſome force, yet to their owne deſtruction, but this is paſſive &amp; of no ſtrength, borne only to ſuffer violence of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
                  <p>But thou willt ſay, There is no word or mention of anie puniſhment appointed for either. True indeed, for the Aogel thought it better to leave it to be thought of, then to expreſſe it. For when he had recorded before, the death of the Meſſias, What puniſhment could have bene ſpoken of, worthie of ſuch a ſin and villanie? Wherfore as vnable to ſet out the greatnes therof, he rather ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth grievouſnes and heinouſnes of it by an ecclypſis or defect of ſpeach, then by an open and plaine terme.</p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:17593:49"/>
                  <p>But as concerning the affaires of the nation yet ſtanding for a time as entire, the fearfull revenging hand of God ſett upon the winge of abominations that maketh deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. Which, then, and what maner of wing is this? <hi>wing</hi> is a militarie word ſignifiing ſome troupe, or band of ſoldiers, ſuch as was the wing of the Iewiſh rebels, when they took vp armes againſt the Romanes: for the Angel doth point at this very time, when he ſaith not ſimply that God will reveng and puniſh the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Iewes, then being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to all that time, ſince they had reiected Chriſt, and obſtinately reteined their aboliſhed ceremonies: but on the winge, he ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when rebellion ſhalbe added to abomination, and the people ſhalbee muſtered and ranked into winges, bandes and troupes: as Ioſephus de bello Iudaico lib. 45. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth it was done, when the zealous (for ſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiratours called themſelves,) whoſe captaines were Eleazar and Iohn, having gathered together a companie of deſperate men, did betake themſelves into the Temple which they made the tower and refuge both of the Civil inteſtine, as alſo of the forraine warres.</p>
                  <p>Theſe troupes of theeves and robbers, allthough all the people conſpiring together, were of the ſame ranke, was certainly this wing of abominations, wholy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact of moſt deſperate, cruel and wicked men, of whom the very Edomites were aſhamed, who being called for their ayde, after they ſaw the barbarouſnes of their felowes and companions, did forſake them preſently, and conveyed themſelves home againe.</p>
                  <p>This was the winge making deſolate with its auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious impudencie and wickednes, and brought ruine, vpon their owne heades, and upon their whole countrie and lawes. Manie thinges make for this expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:17593:50"/>
                  <p>Firſt becauſe deſtruction came upon this wing after Chriſt was cut off, for that is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alcanaph, as it did fall out and happen to the Iewes properly, not to the Romanes. Then againe thoſe thinges which Chriſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for explication ſake Matth. 24.15. This wing ſhould ſtand in the holie place even as theſe robbers in the temple, which they poſſeſſed immediately after they had begun their conſpiracie, and held it to their laſt univerſall ſlaughter.</p>
                  <p>For allthough the whole land of Iudea was the holie place in reſpect of other countries, yet Chriſt ſpake to his diſciples, who by that kind of ſpeech did vnderſtand the Temple as they were accuſtomed commonly. Which yet is more plaine and evident by Mark. 13.14. Who faith this abomination ſhould bee ſett where it ought not, which cannot agree to the Romanes. For Chriſt had now already approved of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> rule over the Iewes, and had commanded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to give to Caeſar thoſe thinges that were Caeſars. Then was it lawfull for them to enforce thoſe mutinous conſpiratours to their duties, what ſhould hinder them from beſieging the citie upon juſt occaſion? when as they made not warre againſt them willingly, but drawne therto againſt their willes and injurioſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked.</p>
                  <p>Laſt of all Chriſt propoundeth this wing of abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſtanding in the holie place as a ſigne to flie out of Iudea, which anie might doe in convenient tyme, whilſt theſe rebels poſſeſſed the Temple a yeare or two before the Romane armie came thither, and there was then very good cauſe to flie, when they could expect no harder meaſure from a conquering enemie, then the citiſens ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred of their domeſticall murderers, but after the citie was beſieged it was too late to think of an eſcape by flight. But Luke ch. 21.20. maketh mention of an armie beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I confeſſe it, but yet notwithſtandinge there
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:17593:50"/> is no leſſe difference betweene this armie and that winge, then between the Romanes and the Iewes, things which differ in the whole ſubjects.</p>
                  <p>Therfore there is not a word of abomination, where there is anie mention of this armie. The one might be well a fit token of the other, ſome part of the time of both exiſting together, wh ch vicinitie and neerneſſe happily occaſioned the expoſitours to confound the thinges themſelves, but they are altogether divers in the nation, countrie and people, to wit, the armie of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, and the abominable winge of the Iewes.</p>
                  <p>The exhortation which foloweth after to flight, we have ſeene out of Mathew from what fontaine it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly floweth. All thinges therfore duly weighed, it ſeemeth to me more probable and fit to expound it of the Iewes then of forreine legions.</p>
                  <p>The other part of puniſhment is upon the nation tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnderfoote, ſuch as it ſhould be from that warre, never able to raiſe vp it ſelfe againe, He ſhal poure, (ſaith he,) vpon the deſolate, even to the conſummation and that determined, which wordes doe ſhewe that it ſhal bee overwhelmed with continuall miſeries, and be brought almoſt vnto nothinge, as we know it was, yet it ſhould have this comfort, that there is a time determined and limited to theſe calamities for ſo meanes the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Nechoretſah.</p>
                  <p>Hence therfore we ſee a twofold deſolation of the place of the people of Ieruſalem, and of the whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The two former did fall into the ſame time. The third indeed from that originall doth yet endure through manie generations.</p>
                  <p>But the deſolation of abomination is a differing thinge from all theſe, a full aboliſhinge of the ceremoniall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe aſwel in reſpect of uſe as right, which the appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted daies will not have begunne at the deſtruction of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:17593:51"/> Ieruſalem: Thefore we muſt ſeek yet further. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles ſeing it is now manifeſt what is abomination: the other word Shomem remaineth to be examined, which expoſitours doe render diverſly, Calvin making aſtonied, Tremelius making deſolate.</p>
                  <p>But for the moſt part it doth alwaies ſignifie paſſively in this active forme, when it not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th action, it is moſtly vſed in piel: which difference Daniel doth diligently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve: for ſpeaking of Antiochus, which made deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by ſetting vp abomination, he noteth him by abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation that maketh deſolate, Meſhomem: ch. 11.31. And againe the ſame forme of the word ſheweth the authours of the calamitie, to come vpon them vpon the wing of abominations, Meſhomim, making deſolate, as in the place lately expounded ch. 9.27. but where he ſpeakes of the people ſuffring deſolation, he uſeth the word Sho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mim, as there he ſhal powre upon the deſolate. In which place both words are vſed Meſhomem, and Sho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mem as rhe figure Antanaclaſis, doth make the difference more apparant.</p>
                  <p>Once I finde it to ſignifie actively as before in ch. 8.13. but out of the more frequent uſe of the word, wee render it paſſively to ſet vp abomination, made deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late.</p>
                  <p>This is the ſumme and effect of the whole ſentence, and from the time, of the daily ſacrifice taken awaie by the death of Chriſt; And of ſetting vp abomination made deſolate, that is to ſaie, of aboliſhing vtterly that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious maner of ſacrificinge; for God had determined that the abrogated vſe of the ceremoniall worſhip ſhould at lenght be vtterly rooted out, ſo as the leaſt trace therof ſhould not remaine. Wherfore when as the ſett time doth conſiſt of two parts, the abrogation of lawfull wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and the rooting out of adulterous.</p>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:17593:51"/>
                  <p>For the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt it is agreed vpon amongſt all, into what time it fell out, neither can the ſecond be obſcure and hidden, if we diligently peruſe the hiſtorie. We know from Chriſt raiſed up from the dead, unto the times of Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſian, this abomination did ſtand in the holie place: holie, both by the firſt inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tution, and alſo by the eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the common people without anie interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
                  <p>But he having ſurprized Ieruſalem, did burne the Temple and deface that place, where alone it was lawful to ſacrifice. Who would not now have thought the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to be made deſolate, but ſoone after it ſhewed it ſelfe againe a litle, vntill Adrian waſted the Iewes with a new ſlaughter, and took from them all hope of recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the holie rubbiſh decaied; For which cauſe they had raiſed a ſharpe warre.</p>
                  <p>Did then the hatred lye buried from this time? after a few yeares it made new broiles againe: for wicked Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian having gotten the government, was the authour and furtherer of the reſtoring the abomination, not only gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinge them libertie to repaire and build the Temple, but alſo by commaunding the charges to be ſupplied out of the publik revenewes of the common wealth. Socr. lib. 3. 20.</p>
                  <p>Neither went they negligently about the buſines when they had this libertie: The Iewes did diligently folow their opportunitie.</p>
                  <p>All thinges were in a readines towards the buildinge: but God did ſodeinly befoole and make void all their labour and impious endevours. An exceding great earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake did ſhake and utterly overthrowe the old foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations which were yet remayninge; or as Theodoret reporteth, themſelves caſt it downe with their owne handes, thinking to build it new from the loweſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations lib. 3. 20.</p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:17593:52"/>
                  <p>Then fire falling downe from heaven, did burne up all their working tooles and inſtruments, ſo as will they nill they, they were conſtreined to deſiſt, and leave off their enterpriſe, &amp; to goe home every one into thoſe contries, whence they had runn together out of every place on all ſides.</p>
                  <p>Cyrill of Ieruſalem maketh mention of this prophecy of Daniel, when the Iewes did firſt ſett upon the worke, which Chriſt hath alſo laid downe in the Goſpels, and ſpake it unto many in private, that now was the time com that a ſtone ſhould not be left upon a ſtone in the temple, but that ſaying of our Saviour ſhould be fulfilled. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was his prediction vaine: The earthquake the very next night confirmed the very truth thereof.</p>
                  <p>Now, that I may conclude with the words of Socrates: <hi>So therfore was the Temple utterly overthrown in stead of the new building, which was prepared.</hi> But now that we have ſeene many and divers overthrowes, which of them ſhall we make the beginning of the account? Aſſuredly the laſt: for a thing is not ſaid to be utterly waſt and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late before it be ſo caſt downe, as it riſeth up no more. As long as it doth a litle after revive againe; It hath a being after a ſort though very troubleſome. When after Iulian therefore nothing mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e was attempted, let us acknowledge from that time the abomination utterly made deſolate.</p>
                  <p>Now then, we have the ſet time of the beginning cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, the laſt open overthrow of all the legall worſhip, which came to paſſe in the dayes of Iulian, about the year 360. For O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uphtius doth caſt the firſt of Conſtantine into the year 304. whereunto if we adde 31 yeares of his reigne, and then 24 of his Sonne Conſtantius, and laſt of all one, and certaine moneths of Iulian, we ſhall finde the Apoſtata to have reigned preciſely at the ſaid time. Let this be ſpoken of the Epache or juſt time of beginning
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:17593:52"/> of the account; the ſpace of time followeth, which can not be concluded in the number of ſo many naturall dayes.</p>
                  <p>No ſuch thing, as is here foretold, did fall out about that time. And the prophet uſeth, when naturall dayes are underſtood to adde, and put to their termes, whereby to know them, as unto evening morning 2300. dayes, ch. 8.14. which bounds being here wanting, we are not to thinke of any other dayes then before of the weekes, whereof every one did ſignifie a weeke of yeares: after which account every day moſt be taken for a yeare. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo alſo but alſo the Iulian yeares, of which ſort were thoſe ſeventy of weekes; whereof if we put 1290 yeares to the times of Iulian the Apoſtata, the fore-appointed time will end, and be out at the yeare 1650. exactly when a time, times, &amp; halfe a time ſhalbe ended as before, verſ. 7. Then ſhall Euphrates be dryed up, that the waye of the Kings of the Eaſt may be prepared, Apoc. 16.12. Then the tydings out of the Eaſt ſhall trouble the King of the North, as before chap. 11.44. Then the Bride, which hath beene baniſhed from the mariage bed ſo many ages and generations ſhall at length, heare, returne, Returne O Shulamite, as we have ſhewed upon Canti. 6.13. Then finally ſhall that voice ring out <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> for the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the Lambe and his wife, Apoca. 19.4.7. for theſe things doe belong to the ſame time, and theſe are the things which ſhall preſently follow the deſtruction of Rome, whoſe laſt deſtinie or ruine is now at hand, as we have made plaine and evident in the Revelation.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:17593:53"/>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 12.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12.</note>
                     </bibl> Bleſſed is he that waiteth and commeth.</q>
                  <p>So is the firſt bound and limit, which being knowne, the ſecond cannot be hard nor hidden, for this of 1335. days doth adde and put to the former 45 years, and doth end at the yeare 1695. The former number did end at the firſt reeling and declining power of the Turkes, this ſecond at the defacing and utter aboliſhing of the ſame: That was perfectly finiſhed together with time, times, and half. This ſhall end together with that ſpace of an houre, and a day, and a moneth, and a yeare, Apoc. 9.15. The tydings before did trouble him from the Eaſt, but now his univerſall ſlaughter ſhal be in the Land of Tzebi, or Iudea, and before th s laſt limit is that ample and large promiſe prefixed: <hi>Bleſſed are they that wait, and doe come vnto it.</hi> And then indeed ſhall all the Saincts be bleſſed, who ſhall have a glorious reſurrection, and be raiſed out of the duſt of deſtruction, and every one of them ſhining like the firmament and ſtarres: for this is the time and limit of that reſurrection, of which before, verſ. 2.3. and Apoc. 26.12, what ſhall be wanting to the chiefeſt fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity on earth, when the Saincts ſhall ſee new Ieruſalem comming downe from Heaven, themſelves inrold citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens therof, doggs excluded, and whatſoever is unclean, hunger and thi ſt to be farre of, all enemies rooted out, and all teares taken away for ever?</p>
                  <p>When I ſay, there ſhall be all theſe things, and infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly many other, which the prophets doe proſecute with admirable pleaſantneſſe of words. Can it be doubted any longer, but then ſhall be indeed that golden age, and higheſt top of holy felicity, and happineſſe, which mortall men may expect, yea or thinke of in this earthly and baſe habitation.</p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:17593:53"/>
                  <p>And this word alone doth falſe up our mindes rather to hope for thoſe things, which the Prophets have ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely ſpoken of this ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter, then to interpret and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound them, as already paſt &amp; fulfilled long agoe. For if we looke back to the death of Antiochus Epiphanes, we have ſhewed already, that the ſpace and number of dayes is altogether unlike &amp; farre diſtant.</p>
                  <p>The decree or Edict of Antiochus his Sonne, wherein he graunted the Iewes their owne Religion freely, doe not reach to the juſt account, as we have ſhewed in verſe 11.</p>
                  <p>Now, if we ſhall caſt the death of Antiochus the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unto the 45. day from that decree, the ſame difference of neceſſity will y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t remaine: but yet ſay I, to graunt the account and calculation to be very juſt, what felicity did follow the death of Antiochus, that the Church might ſo greatly rejoyce therein? except peradventure we ſhall thinke the holy people to be in very great proſperity, while they were oppreſſed with warres under Eupator, 1. Maca. 6.28.29. or that they could triumph greatly when Demetrius was deviſing a ſharp and bitter perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt them by Bachides, Alcimus, and Nicanor, 1. Macab. 7.9.26. eſpecially in his ſecond expedition, when there came ſo great trouble and affliction in Iſrael upon the Iewes, as like was not ſince the time that no prophet was ſeene amongſt them. 1. Macab. 1.9.27.</p>
                  <p>There is no need to record the ambition of the Prieſts, the tyranny of the Romans, the inhumanity and incivility of Herod and the Governours, and that which is farre greateſt of all, the abdication and rejection of the whole nation, for ſo many generations to this day, all which doe of neceſſity carry it, that this full and conſtant felicity of the godly, which the Angel ſpeakes of in this place, can not be of thoſe times.</p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:17593:54"/>
                  <p>How much more ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>telouſly doth the holy Spirit ſpeake, which calle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h all that joy, but a ſmall and litle help, as before in ch 11.34.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Henr. Wolphius lib. de temp.</note>A certaine Godly &amp; Learned Man doth thinke theſe yeares are to be numbred, and to be counted from the overthrow of Ieruſalem by Titus and Veſpaſian, they ate of Chriſt 71. from which beginning the firſt account falleth into the yeare 1361. at which time the Schoole of Prague was found<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d by Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rles King of Bohemia, and did begin to reſiſt and openly to gainſay the errours and tyranny of Antichriſt: The ſecond endeth in the yeare 1406<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when a more cleare light of the Goſpel brako forth, ſo as the Angell here doth pronounce him bleſſed that ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll overlive theſe firſt ſeedes of the Goſpel brought into light againe.</p>
                  <p>But we have declared already, that Titus indeed did deſtroy the Cittie and the Temple, &amp; made a lamentable Havook of the people, ſo as for a time they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreined to leave off their Moſaicall worſhip; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he brought not the laſt giving over of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing, which onely the Angell maketh the ſet time of the beginning.</p>
                  <p>Beſides the knowledge of the Goſpel is a bleſſed thing for all times &amp; ages: but the Angell doth ſpeake of a certaine ſpeciall felicity and bleſſedneſſe, which ſhall come unto the godly, beſides that inward joy of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: Otherwiſe the noting &amp; m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rking out of certaine dayes were in vaine, neither were the promiſed joy of ſo great worth &amp; moment, if the Saincts did enjoy it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes alike.</p>
                  <p>I doe not brethren bring forth their judgements, and refute them any way for to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>epe at them, for I reverence their Godly Labours, and doe honour their great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and knowledge in Chriſt Ieſus: But that no opinions ſhould be any hinderance and prejudicial to the truth,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:17593:54"/> which I am ſure they would have as wel as I. As if the truth lay hidden in the bowels of a hard flint, and cannot be gotten out but by much daſhing and many blowes; yet notwithſtanding I am ſollic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tous and very ſcrupulous herein, leaſt by ſmiting the ſtone, and ſeeking the ſparkle, I ſhould at any time let fall any virulent or venemous ſtro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke upon any mans good name or credit: and I hope my Godly brethren wil likewiſe take in good part this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ude and diſordered worke, whatſoever it is, looking ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to that, which is well and profitablie ſpoken to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it with thankfull mindes, then contemning that which is good for any other defect or unſkilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 13.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13.</note>
                     </bibl> But goe thou thy way till the end bee.</q>
                  <p>Hitherto was the common comfort; that which is proper to Daniel, is in this laſt verſe; The meaning wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is this, as if he ſhould ſay: But then Daniel, goe thy way, and reſt content, that all theſe things ſhall come to paſſe towards or before the end, and although they ſeem to be long delayed, yet the tediouſneſſe thereof ſhall not be grievous unto thee: for thou in the meane time ſhalt yeeld to nature, and go the way of all fleſh, and being freed from the miſeries of this life, ſhalt quietly reſt, and be partaker of that happineſſe, which thoſe doe enjoy which dye in the Lord, and at length alſo ſhall thy body alſo be raiſed up out of the grave, in that Lot and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which God ſhall give unto thee, that thou mayeſt be partaker of unſpeakable joy, with all the reſt of the Saincts, and ſo reigne with Chriſt for ever.</p>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:17593:55"/>
                  <p>This meditation ought to putt away all trouble from the prophet, &amp; to beget in us that moderation and ſtead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe of minde, that although we be tranſported with an eager deſire of this approaching felicity: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding if it be the Lords will ſo to have it, we may wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly depart, and lay downe our earthly Tabernacles.</p>
                  <p>It is a moſt pleaſant thing indeed to ſee and behold Chriſt reigning upon Earth, but there is no cauſe at all why the holy ſoules ſhould envy this pleaſure and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to their Brethren left here below.</p>
                  <p>Let us therefore reſt with quiet mindes in the midſt of the tempeſts and dangers of this World, expecting now ſhortly, either in life or in death, that which is with all votes, and fervent prayers much to be deſired.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>Come Lord Ieſus.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:17593:55"/>
            <head>The Tranſlatour to his Christian friendes in Kent, Suffolke, and elſwhere, wiſheth all health and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppines here and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have bene often requeſted to tranſlate Mr. Brightman vpon Daniel &amp; the Canticles into engliſh, as he is already vpon the revelation. I have at length yeelded to doe one, being both ſhort and pithie, leaving the other to ſuch as have more ſtore of gifts and leiſure, for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons beſt knowne to my ſelfe, which I muſt crave alſo to keep unto my ſelfe: although I confeſſe I would be gladde that all our engliſh Churches ſhould inioy the benefit of the godlie &amp; learned labours of ſuch a worthie Engliſh ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (nay what if I ſhould ſaie, an engliſh prophet, as ſome learned beyond the ſeas have ſtiled him) for as or bleſſed Saviour ſaith, (and it was his owne lot and portion) a prophet is not without honour but in his owne country, and among his owne kindred. Marc. 6.4.</p>
            <p>I have ſeen indeed both Ieſuits and Lutherans abroad, and alſo proteſtants at home, both in pulpits and in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, barking and carping againſt this excellent and worthie man, but I ſpare and pitty them, not anie of them able to doe or ſpeake as he hath done and ſpoken, and manie of them not worthie to cary his bookes after him.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:17593:56"/> It is farre more eaſie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p at a worthie writer then to compile a booke like his, let them eyther mend his, which wilbe a hard talke for them, ſpeak better, or hould their peace.</p>
            <p>He was indeed one of a thouſand, great &amp; gracious manie wais both in life and in learninge, <hi>dum ea docuit quae fecit? &amp; ea fecit quae docuit, &amp; verba vertebat in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera.</hi> He taught that he did practiſe, and did practiſe that he taught, and ſo turned wordes into workes. He was a great Artiſt and a great linguiſt. He had good ſkill in all arts and tongues needfull for a compleat de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, even in ſong alſo, (vocall muſick being the beſt) till his more weightie ſtudies cald him from the mayde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to divinitie their miſtreſſe, wherin he excelled and ſhined above manie of his fellowes, all that then lived with him in Queens Colledge in Cambridge, wherof he was a fellowe, doe very well knowe. He ſhined every waie, and was a Brightman indeed anſwerable to his name, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>vir ſplendidus,</hi> a bright man, in his life ſhining to all that converſed with him, and in his deep learning &amp; knowledge ſhining to all that heard his learned catechizinge, common places, and lectures in the colledge, or his ſermons in the countrie in Bedford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aquila non capit muſcas.</hi> Eagle like he ſoareth aloft catching no flies but great and high matters; he doth not with the lambe wade in the ſhallow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, obvious and playn places, but with the Elephant he ſwimmeth and helps other to ſwimme ſafely over the deepeſt and darkeſt places of the whole canonicall ſcriptures, as Iohns reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, Salomons ſonge, and Daniels obſcureſt viſion in 11.12.</p>
            <p>Some may think he did <hi>altum ſapere</hi> and beare to high aboue his reach and capacitie, and therfore hee the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:17593:56"/> Auſtr. Lutheran applyeth the ſpeach of Feſtus to Paul Act. 24. to him untruely, but thoſe that did well know him, and the great meaſure of meeknes and humilitie that God had graced him withall, would not think that he did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſaith very elegantlie in that eloquent exhortation Rom. 12.3. <hi>Jmum humilitatis, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum divinitatis,</hi> The depth of humilitie is the height of divinitie: the lower in or ſelves, the higher with God, as himſelfe ſpeaketh Eſai, 57.15. though he be high and loftie and dwelleth in the highe and holie place, yet he wil dwell alſo with the contrite and humble ſpirit, &amp; vnto ſuch wil he be a guide and teach them his wayes and counſels. Pſ. 25.9.14.</p>
            <p>And therfore I doe not doubt, but God revealed much vnto him &amp; let him ſee a great deale more into theſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall &amp; darke paſſages, then manie other of his deere ſervants, that ſo he might reveal &amp; open them to others: for as he freely received ſo he freely gave.</p>
            <p>But whither will my love carry me? I refraine: his owne works ſhal praiſe him abundauntly; which becauſe being in latin, the greateſt part of our countrimen doe not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand. I have made his ſhort expoſition of Daniel to ſpeak engliſh unto them, that none maie be deprived of the benefit of his godlie labours.</p>
            <p>It is pitie ſuch a bright ſhining candle ſhould be put under the bed or buſhel, but to be ſet ſo as all may ſee &amp; enioy the light therof. Math. 5.15. He hath ſo cleered that pointe of the Iewes vocation, which the Apoſtle caſteth a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Rom. 11.33. in theſe latter times after the overthrowe of their laſt &amp; greateſt enemie the Turks, as I have not ſeene in anie writer the like. He goeth beyond the ſtreine and againſt the ſtreame of the moſt interpreters, who goe about for the moſt part to reſtreine
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:17593:57"/> all in Daniel to the firſt comming of Chriſt and doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre all to Antiochus, or to the Romanes: which cannot be, for neither of them come to their endes in Iudea, or the glorious holie mountaine, as the Turk ſhal doe. Dan. 11.45.</p>
            <p>Daniel having in the former part of this chapter 11. laied downe their other enemies the Perſians verſ. 2. the Grecians, cheifly Alexander. verſ. 3. and his 4 captaines ſucceeding verſe 4. which came eſpecially to two princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall heades: the Lagidans in Egypt, whom he calleth the Kinges of the South, as ſtanding South from Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea verſ. 5. and the Seleucidans in Syria, whom he calleth the Kinges of the North, verſ. 6. &amp;c. to the 36.</p>
            <p>Then and there he commeth to the three laſt enemies of the Iewes, the Romanes, which had clipped the winges of Antiochus in the 30. verſe, till at the end their owne eagles winges were alſo clipped by the Saracens &amp; Turkes in verſ. 40. the one like a doſſing beaſt doe puſh ſore at him, the other comming againſt him like a whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winde that cannot be reſiſted, overfloweth, beares and beates downe all before it, entreth into Iudaea, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious land, which had bene then a longe time the cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit of the world in the midſt of their enemies, Babilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Perſians, Grecians, Lagidans, Seleucidans, Romans, Saracens and now at this daie the Turkes, the laſt, though not the leaſt of their adverſaries, which ſhalbee troubled with the tydinges of the eaſterne and northerne Iewes converſion, which ſhal make him to march out furiouſly againſt them like another Iehu 2 king. 9.20. though not with like ſucceſſe, but he ſhal com to his end there, in the holie land and glorious mountaine, and note ſhal help him, for who can help and hold him vp whom God wil hinder and caſt downe?</p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:17593:57"/>
            <p>Then followethe joyfull returne and reſurrection of the Iewes: who lay as dead for almoſt ſeventeen hundred yeares in chap. 12. which if it be not meant of them, there is litle comfort for them in the whole prophecy, which was the Prophets maine intention and principall drift and ſcope, <hi>Oculus adſcopum,</hi> our eye muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes at the mark and ſcope, if we mean to hit the white and right meaning, and ſo the Apoſtle Paul doth call their calling and receaving unto grace, life from the dead, Rom. 11.15. whereunto moſt ſweetly agreeth the prophet Ezekiel from the 37. chapter. to the end of his prophecye in the laſt 12. chapters, firſt ſetting downe their converſion in the firſt 14. verſes of the 37. where the dead and dry bones ſcattered come together agayne and live.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly the vnyting and joyning together againe the ten tribes with the two, from the 15. verſ. to the end.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the deſtruction of Gog, and all their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in the 38. and 39. chapters.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, and laſtly, we have a heavenly new prophecie concerning the glorious and Chriſtian Church of the Iewes, whereof Chriſt himſelf was the builder, in the 9 laſt chapters, beginning with a very ſolemne charge, for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend attention, and a ſweete carriage, and demeanour of all parts, inward and outward, as of hart, eyes, and eares. 40.4. And alſo concluding with the new and laſting name thereof, not Ieruſalem, as of olde now antiquated, but <hi>Iehovah Shammah,</hi> the Lord is and will be there for ever, as being the truth of the former type, repreſented by the temple, Pſalm 132.14. This is my reſt for ever, here will I dwell, for I have deſired it.</p>
            <p>Thus have I briefly in a word epitomiſed and abrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged this learned expoſition for thee: He ſhall now ſpeak unto thee in thine owne mothers tongue and native lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. He will bring that to thine eares, which happily
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:17593:58"/> thou didſt never heare of before: Make much of ſuch faithfull expoſitours, and praie to God to increaſe the number of ſuch learned interpreters, as may help thee to ſee and vnderſtand ſuch myſticall viſions and revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of God, and that he would in his due time bring downe thoſe two mayne enemies of his goſpell and his people, the Romane Antichriſt in his old Rome, and the eaſterne Gog and Magog in his new Rome or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, who would ſoon fall of his owne Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane ponderous weight, if he were not ſupported by Romiſhe idolatrie: And let not vs proteſtants by our ſcandalous lives and converſations be anie hinderaunce to the calling and comming on of our farre diſtant brethren the Iewes, but help forward, what we maie their effectuall vocation, by frequent and fervent prayer for them, and dayly crucifying of ſin, which crucified the Lord of glorie both theirs and ours, and ſo together with joynt conſent ſet forth the purity of Gods worſhip: and celebrate his prayſes unto the full and finall end and conſummation of all thinges.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17593:58"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
